<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Family religion in three letters to a friend / by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13577348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13577348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60133)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1049:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Family religion in three letters to a friend / by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>114, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with print show-through and slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Family --  Religious life.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Family Religion, IN THREE LETTERS TO A FRIEND.</p>
            <p>By JOHN SHOWER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the Angel in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:100460:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100460:2"/>
            <head>Of Family Religion.</head>
            <head type="sub">The FIRST LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Subſtance of what I lately preach'd concerning <hi>Family Religion and Worſhip,</hi> I now ſend you, at your Deſire, in <hi>Three Letters.</hi> The <hi>Firſt</hi> recommends the Duty with the Grounds of it: The <hi>Second</hi> anſwers ſome Objections, and Difficulties as to the Practice: The <hi>Third</hi> directs the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Performance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Succeſs of theſe plain Diſcourſes, through the Bleſſing of Heaven, was beyond Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation; to bring the daily Worſhip of God into ſeveral Houſes, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was none; and to have it conſtant where it was perform'd but ſeldom, and uncertainly; and to be now every Day, inſtead of once a Week,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100460:3"/>and every Morning and Evening in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Prayer at <hi>Night</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Divers of our Brethren in this City can ſay the like, and I hope more, of the good Effects of our Agreement to preach on this Subject about the ſame time. It was ſeaſonable to more than we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined: And there may be divers who have ſince begun to worſhip God in their Families, who are aſham'd to own that they neglected it ſo long. Tho not a few, with humble Thankfulneſs to God, have acknowledg'd their Conviction, and Reformation of that Neglect. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Servants and Apprentices aſſure us, that God is now daily worſhip'd, and the Holy Scriptures read in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies where they live, who had no ſuch thing before, ſave only on the Lord's-Day.</p>
            <p>I had no thoughts at firſt of publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing on this Subject, becauſe there is a great deal to this purpoſe already printed in
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Gurnal<hi>'s Chriſtian Warfare. Mr.</hi> Swinnock's <hi>Chriſtian Man's Calling. Mr.</hi> Baxter<hi>'s Directory. Yet Supplem. to the Morning-Exerciſe at</hi> Cripplegate. <hi>Some of Dr.</hi> Manton<hi>'s Sermons. Mr.</hi> O.H<hi>'s Family-Altar,</hi> &amp;c.</note> other Practical Books, from whence I have had Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100460:3"/>and ſome others of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I did hope would be prevailed with to print their Sermons, (and am glad to hear that it is now doing, or reſolved to be done.) But you, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who do conſtantly attend my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, do hope to profit further by the Peruſal of thoſe things, which in the Delivery were of ſome uſe.</p>
            <p>This is reaſon enough to me for appearing again ſo ſoon in Print. I may ſay in this caſe as one (whoſe Name I honour) doth upon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a like Occaſion, that as in all the Removes of my Life, I have been ſtill led to that place, which was moſt remote from my own Thoughts, and never deſign'd or contriv'd by my ſelf; So it hath been, as to what I have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; there hath been (for the moſt part) ſome unexpected Providence, and Occaſion ſufficient to ſatisfy me, that I ought to do it; while thoſe Writings, which I moſt affected, have been ſtifled in the Conception; and thoſe which I have moſt labour'd in, are like to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Duſt: Hereby I am made to know that God is the Diſpoſer of all.</p>
            <p>In this firſt Letter I ſhall collect the Subſtance of what may <hi>recommend</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100460:4"/>
               <hi>prove</hi> the Duty of <hi>Family Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip;</hi> at leaſt what I think is <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> to do ſo, tho it be not all that can be ſaid. I begin with the Neceſſity of it, in order to <hi>a National Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not a more common Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Complaint, than the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Corruption of Manners, and the Prevalency of Debauchery, and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion among us. We muſt ſhut our Eyes, and ſtop our Ears, if we are not acquainted with it: Who is not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the Juſtice and Truth of ſuch a Complaint? All ſerious People pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to bewail the want of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and many are apprehenſive of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Judgments upon that Account. But what Hope of <hi>a National Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> if it begin not in <hi>Families?</hi> If they, who have the Care and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe leſſer Societies, will not faithfully do their part; neither Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or Miniſters can expect Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in doing Theirs. Nations will be wicked, and Churches will be corrupt, and Cities will abound with all manner of Impurity; if particular Families, out of which the Members are all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, be diſordered and irregular.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100460:4"/>
            <p>They who are not taught the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Fear of God betimes, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if they run into Atheiſm and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery as they grow up. That ſo many are thus corrupted in Principles, and Converſation, muſt needs be very much owing to the Neglect and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of Parents, and Heads of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. Reformation muſt therefore begin in Families: And a whole Street would ſoon be made clean, by every Man's Care as to his own Houſe, and ſweeping before his own Door. The Pſalmiſt began that in his own Family, which he deſign'd ſhould reach to his whole Kingdom: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</p>
            <p>Is it ſtrange, if they who have lived many Years in ſuch Families, where God was not worſhipped, where there was little or no Concern about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, (it may be not ſo much as the Form, and the Shew of it) if they are ignorant and careleſs, diſſolute and profane, when they come to have Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of their own? If they be as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſolicitous for the Souls under their Care, as their own Parents and Maſters were of <hi>theirs,</hi> during their Minority? If there be no reading the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, no inſtructing of Children and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100460:5"/>Servants, no Prayer and Praiſe offered to God in the Family, <hi>as ſuch;</hi> how unlikely is it, that ſuch who are brought up in their Youth in ſuch Houſes, ſhould afterwards be Exemplary for Religion in their own?</p>
            <p>It lies more upon Parents and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to recover, and preſerve ſerious Godlineſs in the World, than either upon the Civil Magiſtrate, or the moſt diligent and faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, in their places. And whence can we hope for any <hi>uſeful Magiſtrates,</hi> or <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters,</hi> if they are not formed to be capable of being <hi>ſuch,</hi> by the wiſe and good Inſtruction of holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the Bleſſing of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, in their tender Years? It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, they are like to profit little by the preaching of the Word, if they have not Underſtanding and prepared Minds, by the Inſtructions of Parents and Maſters at home; at leaſt little in compariſon of others who have had that Advantage. One great reaſon why People do not better underſtand Sermons, and profit more by them, is, becauſe they never well underſtood their Catechiſm.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100460:5"/>
            <p>It is in vain therefore to talk againſt the Badneſs of the Times, and the Looſeneſs of the Age, unleſs you will reſolve that Reformation ſhall begin at home; and every one be at the pains to Reform his own little Family.</p>
            <p>It is from thence that Wickedneſs doth ſpread and diffuſe it ſelf over a whole Kingdom. One ignorant, athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical, erroneous, or wicked Family may do much to corrupt, defile and deſtroy ſeveral others, when the Branches thereof are ſeparated: As by a Son going into one Family, and a Daughter into another, and a Servant into a third: They carry and communicate their evil Principles and Cuſtoms, and Prejudices, to the Infection of others. It cannot reaſonably be expected that Perſons, when they come abroad in the World, ſhould ordinarily prove better than their Education. Whereas, as one obſerves, a Religious Family is, on the contrary, a diffuſive Bleſſing, like a Stock of Bees, which ſends forth Swarms and Honey into Neighbouring Parts. Eſpecially as the Members here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of come hereafter to have Families of their own. Therefore to ſhut Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion out of Families, or not promote
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100460:6"/>it there, is the means to thruſt it out of the World.</p>
            <p>This has been obſerved by the very Pagans, as the proper way for a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man to be <hi>a Publick Good,</hi> and ſerviceable to the Welfare of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>ordering things well at home,</hi> with Wiſdom and Care, in his own Houſe and Family. And there is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any thing whereby ſo much Evil is done to the <hi>Publick,</hi> as by the Careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Parents in the Inſtruction of their Children, and the Negligence, or ill Examples of Maſters with reſpect to their Servants. Among ſome of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> a Penalty has been laid upon the Parents, when the Children were ill-conditioned: and they might be ſued in the Courts of Judicature, if they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the Education of their Children.</p>
            <p>And how much the Safety, Pleaſure and Comfort of our Lives depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faithful Diſcharge of Relative Duties, Experience will teach us. What greater Comfort can a Parent or a Maſter have, than to ſee the Succeſs of his Endeavours for the Good of thoſe under his Roof? A natural Parent may ſay it, as well as a ſpiritual one, <hi>I have no greater Joy than to ſee my Children
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100460:6"/>walking in the Truth.</hi> It is ſaid of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Heb.</hi> 11.9. that he dwelt in Tents with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob; Heirs with him of the ſame Promiſe.</hi> How comfortable is it when Father, Son and Grandſon, are all Heirs of the ſame promiſed Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Eſpecially if God bleſs your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours towards it, that they who come from your Loins may ſerve the Lord. There is a double Bleſſing where the Father is Godly, and the Son ſo likewiſe. To ſee them alive to God, who were dead in Sin, will revive the Heart of a Religious Parent, as it did old <hi>Jacob</hi>'s, to know that his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> was <hi>alive.</hi> To have Wife and Children bear the Image of God, and our Servants to obey, and ſerve, and pleaſe their Heavenly Maſter; and by our Faithfulneſs, and Care, and Diligence to be brought to know, and love, and worſhip, and honour him, and be accepted with him; What an unſpeakable Delight muſt this be! when the Savour of Religion deſcends from the Head to all the Members of the Family, as the precious Ointment, pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Head of <hi>Aaron,</hi> ran down to the Skirts of his Garments. You then may, and will love them with a higher
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100460:7"/>kind of Love, than bare natural Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, you will <hi>love</hi> your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, Wives, and Children, and holy Relations, with <hi>another ſort of Love</hi> than other Perſons do theirs. It is a more fervent, more pure, more faithful, more comfortable Love, which is ſuperadded by Religion, and reſults from their Love to God, and Participation of his Image. You love them, as the Friends and Brethren of Chriſt, as Heirs of the ſame Inheritance, as begotten again to a Divine Life by the ſame Spirit, as born of the ſame Immortal Seed of the Word, as nouriſh'd by the ſame Spiritual Food, as under the ſame Bond of the Covenant, as of one Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith, as Souldiers under the ſame Colours and Banner of Chriſt, as called to the ſame bleſſed Hope of the Goſpel, as Travellers to the ſame Heavenly Country, and Coheirs of the ſame glorious, everlaſting Kingdom. You cannot love your unſanctified Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations in this manner, whatever Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or Civil Bonds of Union there may be between you and them. It will pleaſe you doubtleſs, to ſee them thrive and proſper in the World, whom you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100460:7"/>tenderly love; but it muſt much more do ſo, to ſee them faithful to God, live to his Glory, and ripen for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Whether you live or die, you may then comfortably reſign them, and truſt them with God, who loves them better than you, and will be ſure to take care of them. With what Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure can you think of the Sin and Miſery which they eſcape? What Wickedneſs ſuch a Child would elſe have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted on Earth? and what Torments he muſt have endured in Hell, if he had been wicked? Their Love, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Obedience to you, (which the Grace of God will teach them) will alſo add to your Joy; in your Health and Sickneſs, or old Age, they will pray for you. And if they die, you can look forward to the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Happineſs of their Souls, as well as your own, and the hopes of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with Comfort in the Day of Reckoning.</p>
            <p>And what an Honour is it to any Family, to have ſerious Godlineſs tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from Father to Son, and from the Son to the Grand-Child? To be able to ſay, My God, and my Father's God, and my Grand-father's God?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100460:8"/>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. as <hi>Pliny</hi> reports,
<note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> on <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. p. 551.</note> it was counted a great Honour and Felicity, that in one Family of the <hi>Fabii,</hi> there were three Preſidents of the Senate one after another; and in one Houſe of <hi>Curio</hi>'s, there were three Orators one after another.</p>
            <p>Beſides, how Beautiful and Pleaſant a Thing is a Religious Well-ordered Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily! How Comfortable is it to dwell in ſuch an Houſe? Where God is Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped, and his Laws obſerved, and his Day ſanctified, his Word read, his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority owned, and his Laws made the Rule! Where it is an Honour, and not a Reproach to eſchew Evil and do Good! God promiſes to bleſs the Habitations of the Juſt, and how ſweet will his Preſence be unto ſuch! Whereas, to live in a Houſe where the Name of God is never uſed, but in jeſt, or ſcorn, or prophane Oaths; where the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are as ſo many Brutes, that live from day to day, as if they had no Souls to ſave, no World but this to mind, and no Expectations beyond the Grave; where Worldlineſs and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, filthy Talk, and Intemperance,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100460:8"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have infected Superiours and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours. Who would dwell in ſuch a Houſe? There cannot generally be Peace and Union, Love and Concord in ſuch Mens Dwellings. Family Jars, Contentions and Sorrows are occaſioned by Sin, which Family Religion would do much to prevent and cure.</p>
            <p>If Children are a Grief to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Thorns in their Eyes, (as a Wicked Son is the Calamity and Shame of his Father, and Heavineſs to his Mother;) they may thank themſelves, as of their own Planting: if they did not with Love and Diligence, with Wiſdom and Faithfulneſs ſeek their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. If Servants neglect their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to you, how can you wonder, when you have neglected yours to them? You muſt bear the Fruit of their Sin, if you do not teach them the Principles of Religion, which ſhould make them better; and teach them to keep a good Conſcience by giving them your own Example. But if your Endeavours ſhould not ſucceed for their Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Salvation, you will yet have much more Peace than otherwiſe; as having done what you could towards it. Whereas, without ſuch Indeavours,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100460:9"/>it muſt be an afflictive piercing Thought when any of them <hi>Die,</hi> or when you your ſelves muſt; to conſider that you did no more to prevent their Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and that ſuch and ſuch, through your Unfaithfulneſs, are like to Periſh for ever, who ſprang from your Loins, or went to Hell out of your Houſe.</p>
            <p>Moreover, what Evidence can you have of your own Piety, and Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards God, if you do not thus indeavour the Spiritual and Eternal Good of thoſe under your Charge? <hi>Abraham</hi> would command his Children, and his Houſhold after him, that they ſhould fear the Lord. <hi>Joſhua</hi> reſolves to engage all his Houſe to ſerve the true God with him; though a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and a Great Man, did not think it beneath him to own Religion before all the World, and endeavour to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it. He would not ſerve the True God <hi>alone,</hi> if he could prevail with Others to join with him: Propoſeth his own Example to the whole Nation; and that as far as in him lay all his Family at leaſt ſhould be Religious. <hi>Cornelius</hi> was a devout Man, and feared God with all his Houſe. We may, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being uncharitable, ſuſpect the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100460:9"/>ſoundneſs of their Religion; who are unconcerned for the ſpreading of it in their Families. How is it conſiſtent with Faithfulneſs to your own Souls; to have litle or no Care concerning theirs? If you are wanting in uſing the means for their Salvation, you ſhake the ground of Hope concerning your own.</p>
            <p>And Family Prayer and Inſtruction, and the Holy Examples of Good Men in their Houſes, is one of the <hi>Firſt Means</hi> which God commonly makes uſe of to Convince, and Turn, and Sanctifie ſuch as were Ignorant and Carnal. At leaſt, Education making the firſt Impreſſion on their Minds, whatever Change may be afterwards made by free Converſation, ſomewhat of the firſt good Tincture is like to abide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordinarily</hi> I ſay, through the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, this may be hoped for; tho it muſt be confeſſed, that where the Advantages of Education are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>improved, it is obſerved, many of the <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> who have been bred in good Families, prove worſe than others. If they forſake God, he hath ſaid, <hi>He will forſake them, and caſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100460:10"/>them off for ever.</hi> It is a Judicial Act in God, when Children caſt off the God of their Fathers. If they turn Apoſtates, they many times run deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into Sin, and further from God than others, as <hi>Cain, Cham, Iſhmael, Eſau, Eli</hi>'s Sons, <hi>Abſolom,</hi> yea <hi>Solomon, Rehoboam, Manaſſeh,</hi> and few compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively recovered. The Light and Means they ſin againſt provokes God to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them. Upon the ſame grounds we may give an account, why there are more <hi>Atheiſts</hi> in ſuch places, where the Chriſtian Religion is profeſſed, and the Power of it rejected, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong any other ſort of Men, even than there were among the <hi>Heathens</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For
<note n="*" place="bottom">See to this purpoſe, Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> of Spiritual-Mindedneſs. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</note> God hath deſigned to <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his Word above all his Name,</hi> above all other ways of the Revelation of himſelf to the Children of Men. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where this is deſpiſed and rejected, <hi>Reaſon</hi> or the Light of Nature ſhall not have the ſame Power and Efficacy, as on them who never enjoyed the Light of the Goſpel, or ſo much of it. From the ſame Reaſon, that the Children of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100460:10"/>Profeſſors are ſometimes irrecoverably Profligate, there is more <hi>Common Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſty and Juſtice</hi> to be found among ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilized <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> than among falſe and degenerate Chriſtians. Their Hearts are judicially hardened, and their Eyes blinded. And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Goſpel Light muſt needs beget, and leave on the Mind ſuch a depraved corrupt Habit, as cannot but incline unto the worſt of Evils. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. And as all <hi>Atheiſm</hi> ſprings from a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> not to ſee things Eternal, and inviſible to Senſe; where-ever Men are reſolved not to ſee, the greater the light is which ſhines about them, the faſter they muſt cloſe their Eyes. It is not therefore to the <hi>Diſparagement,</hi> but <hi>Honour of the Goſpel,</hi> that ſo many avow themſelves to be <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> in thoſe places where the Truth of it is known and profeſſed: For none can have any inclination thereto, till they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Goſpel, which immediately expoſeth them to the worſt of Evils. They take ſhelter from their Fears in downright <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> which alone pretends to give them ſecurity againſt the Light of Divine Revelation. And what means can be uſed for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100460:11"/>of ſuch? The moſt rational Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to prove the Being and Exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of God, may be of good uſe to ſhame, and expoſe their fooliſh Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But Men under the Power of Atheiſtical Thoughts, are inſnared <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them</hi> by a Love of ſome Luſt, and a deſire to live ſecurely in Sin; and no Arguments from Reaſon, are like to prove an effectual Cure to the Predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant Love of Sin, and an Habitual Courſe in it, where Men have rejected the Means and Motives unto that end declared in Divine Revelation.</p>
            <p>Parents however have ſufficient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to hope for ſucceſs in their faithful Endeavours: There be many can ſpeak of God, and praiſe him as their <hi>Fathers God,</hi> from Age to Age. If they neglect their Duty to Children, (which is ordinarily the reaſon, why ſo many miſcarry) they cannot challenge God, for not perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Covenant-Promiſe, but muſt condemn themſelves. But whatever the Succeſs be, every Parent, and Head of Family is obliged to Honour God, and Promote Religion, and do what good he can for the Souls of others, within his Sphere.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100460:11"/>
            <p>This all in their ſeveral Places are bound to endeavour, as they have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity. You muſt be faithful to Chriſt and his Intereſt in every <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and in every <hi>Capacity.</hi> If you are obliged to ſerve and worſhip God in a ſingle Capacity, as Private Perſons; by virtue of the ſame Dedication of your ſelves to Him, you are bound to ſerve and Honour him <hi>in every Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as Husbands, Parents, Maſters, and Heads of Families, in every State and Condition, according to your Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And by Family Prayer and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God hath greater Honour, than by Secret Prayer; tho therein you may more particularly, and largely expreſs the ſtate of your own Soul.</p>
            <p>And of how great Conſequence, to <hi>the Eternal Salvation,</hi> or <hi>Ruine of Souls,</hi> is your Care, or Unfaithfulneſs herein! How can you ſerve the Devil more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, than by furthering the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all under your Roof, through the neglect of your Duty to them? And without giving them Aſſiſtance, and Help to a Holy Life, they will have continual Temptations to Sin. In that Houſe wherein God is not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, honoured, and worſhiped, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100460:12"/>Devil's Intereſt will prevail. And ſince they have an Everlaſting Happineſs to attain, and Endleſs Miſery to eſcape, they will have little reaſon to thank you, for whatever elſe you can teach them, or do for them; if you will not inſtruct them, and aſſiſt them in <hi>This,</hi> their moſt Important Concern.</p>
            <p>It might be hoped, that if <hi>Parents</hi> did their part in the uſe of God's firſt appointed Means, to ſanctify their Children; he would uſually bleſs their Indeavours in order to his ſaving Grace. And when ſerious Religion is once got into a Family, it has been obſerved, for your Encouragement, that ordinarily the Grace of God doth not ſoon leave it: tho there may be ſome ſad Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet it appears many times again in Grand-Children, and Great Grand-Children; as in the Seed of good <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat</hi> and others, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.21.22. Chap. <hi>Jotham</hi> had <hi>Ahaz,</hi> but <hi>Ahaz</hi> had <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> and if not in the direct Line, yet collaterally. So that by this means you may tranſmit Religion to Poſterity, from Generation to Generation; as Sin is propagated from Father to Son, and from one wicked Family diffuſed to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others: And you perpetuate your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100460:12"/>own Name and Honour too; for God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Children occaſion their Parents to be called to Memory. By beholding <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi>'s Piety, the Apoſtle is minded to remember his Mother, and Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, <hi>Eunice</hi> and <hi>Lois,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.5. <hi>When I call to remembrance the unfeigned Faith that is in thee, which dwelt firſt in thy Grandmother</hi> Lois, <hi>and thy Mother</hi> Eunice; <hi>and I am perſwaded that in thee alſo.</hi> The Piety and Care of holy Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men is recorded with Honour, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.1. <hi>Behold a certain Diſciple was there, named</hi> Timotheus, <hi>the Son of a certain Woman which was a Jeweſs, and believed; but his Father was a Greek.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is the fingular Uſefulneſs of the holy Government of Families to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the World, and deſtroy the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Intereſt of the Devil, that there is hardly any thing that Men have more Objections againſt, or more Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Excuſes to extenuate the Nog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of their <hi>Duty,</hi> or perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves it is <hi>none,</hi> than in this Caſe. One of the moſt common and prevailing Cavils is this, That if they bring their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants to <hi>the Publick Worſhip,</hi> to be taught by the Miniſter, there is <hi>no poſitive, expreſs Scripture</hi> for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100460:13"/>of God in their Families, to call them together, to pray with them, and read the Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in how many other caſes is it granted, that the want of a poſitive ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Command will not conclude ſuch or ſuch a Thing to be no Duty? The Baptiſm of Infants, the Sanctification of the firſt Day of the Week as the Chriſtian Sabbath, the Admiſſion of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the Lord's-Table, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may be given, which may be proved to be Matter of Duty, without poſitive expreſs Command. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is ſaid to confound the <hi>Jews</hi> dwelling at <hi>Damaſcus, proving out of the Scriptures, that</hi> Jeſus <hi>was the</hi> Chriſt; <hi>Acts</hi> 9.21. it muſt be by the Harmony of the Holy Scriptures, and by Deductions from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Texts: for he did not bring any one particular Scripture out of the Old Teſtament, to prove in ſo many Letters, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Nor did our Lord in his Proof of the Reſurrection of the Dead againſt the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> out of the Old Teſtament, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37. There are no ſuch words as the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead</hi> mention'd in that Paſſage, from which he proves it. <hi>I am the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100460:13"/>
            <p>'Tis an Argument of a very perverſe Mind, to inſiſt ſo much upon poſitive Scriptural Proof of that as our Duty, which muſt be acknowledged to be ſo much for our Benefit and Advantage, and for the Publick Good.</p>
            <p>There is reaſon enough to believe, that they who pretend there is <hi>no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Scripture</hi> for this kind of Duty, would little mind it, if there were never ſo many, and never ſo expreſs. for if Men were true to God, and their own Souls, in thoſe things for which we have the moſt poſitive, and expreſs, and repeated Authority of the Holy Scriptures; they would not raiſe ſuch a Scruple. There is an expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Repent of Sin, and to Believe on Chriſt, and to make your Calling and Election ſure; to Redeem your Time, and walk Circumſpectly; to do good unto all; to pray every where, and all ſorts of Prayer; and in every Calling, Station and Relation, therein to abide with God; to live by Faith upon the inviſible World; to prepare to die, and to remember the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, before which we muſt be made to ſtand, to anſwer for all we have received and done in the Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100460:14"/>there are <hi>Expreſs Scriptures</hi> about theſe things: And did we believe them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them, and obey them; we ſhould ſoon ſee Reaſon, and Evidence ſufficient for all that Duty of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and promoting Religion in our Families, which I would now preſs.</p>
            <p>I know there be ſome Arguments uſed from Scripture upon this Subject, which many think will not conclude all that which they are brought to prove. As that becauſe we read of <hi>the Church of God</hi> in ſuch a Man's Houſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. (when it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there were no common Aſſemblies of Chriſtians at <hi>Rome</hi>) that therefore every Houſe ſhould be as a <hi>Church,</hi> by daily Prayer and Praiſe to God: For the Houſe of God is <hi>an Houſe of Prayer,</hi> and a Church is God's Houſe. I will not urge this, becauſe a Houſe might be called a Church, only on the Account of the Church ſometimes aſſembling for Divine Worſhip in ſuch a Man's Houſe. I grant the ſmalleſt Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Faithful met to worſhip God, may bear the Name of a Church. However, I do not believe this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, becauſe I believe it true of many in this City and Nation, (and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100460:14"/>wiſh I had no ground for it) that they have had frequent Meetings in their Houſes for Prayer and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and divers Chriſtians have reſpr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Worſhip of God there; and yet the Maſter of the Family lived in the neglect of <hi>Family Prayer,</hi> and the daily Worſhip of God in his Houſe.</p>
            <p>Neither will I urge the Example of our Saviour Chriſt, his praying with his Diſciples: Though much may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from his Pattern, as having a Family, whereof he was the Maſter, and his Twelve Apoſtles Members. (Conſtant Reſidence in one Houſe is not neceſſary to conſtitute the Relation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Head of a Family, and the Members of it.) We read of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing 'em, praying with 'em, and praiſing God, by ſinging together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I will not lay too much ſtreſs on this Example, becauſe though our Bleſſed Lord did occaſionally pray with his Diſciples, as we find in ſeveral places of the Goſpel-Hiſtory; yet his Caſe and ours are vaſtly different. What was ſuitable for his Diſciples, was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for him. He could not ordinarily be their Mouth in Prayer, for what they daily needed: He could not for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100460:15"/>himſelf ask the Forgiveneſs of Sin, and the Mortification of Luſt, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is enough from the Holy Scriptures, to convince thoſe that will ſeriouſly conſider it, of the Duty of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily Religion,</hi> and Prayer as a part of it. For Inſtance, we read of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> that he reſolves for himſelf and Family, <hi>I and the Men of my Houſe will ſerve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord:</hi> That is, the Men who dwelt with him in his Houſe. And we read of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Acts 10.2. that <hi>he was a devout Man, one that feared God with all his Houſe, and gave much Alms to the People, and prayed always.</hi> He was a <hi>Roman</hi> Captain over the <hi>Italian</hi> Band, which attended the <hi>Roman</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour's Perſon as his Life-guard, and therefore probably of that Nation. This <hi>Cornelius</hi> is ſaid to be a <hi>Devout Man.</hi> Whether he were a Proſelyte to the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> or no, is doubtful, be ſure not <hi>a Proſelyte of the Covenant,</hi> or of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for ſuch were Circumciſed. If he were an Uncircumciſed Proſelyte, or <hi>a Proſelyte of the Gate,</hi> he was not incorporated into the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> had a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion firſt to authorize him to go to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100460:15"/>him. And the Chriſtians of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion expreſt their Reſentment for his Converſation with him, till they knew his Warrant, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.3. Yet this Roman, this Souldier, this Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was accepted of God, as being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to believe in Chriſt, aſſoon as he ſhould be revealed to him. He was a devout and good Man; and not only good himſelf, but choſe ſuch to be in his Family, as feared God. He was full of good Works, and conſtant in <hi>Prayer:</hi> and God teſtified his Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of him, <hi>Thy Prayers, and thine Alms are come up as a Memorial before God,</hi> Verſ. 4. <hi>Of a Truth I perceive,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>that God is no reſpecter of Perſons; but in every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, ſhall be accepted,</hi> Verſ. 39. Here is a ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Example of a devout Souldier, a devout Roman, ſpreading Religion in his Family; One that <hi>feared God with all his Houſe,</hi> and <hi>prayed always.</hi> The Fear of God is an uſual Expreſſion, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of <hi>all Divine Worſhip,</hi> 2 Kings 17.36, 37. Let all the Earth <hi>worſhip him,</hi> Pſal. 66.4. Let all the Earth <hi>fear him,</hi> Pſal. 67.7. And <hi>Prayer</hi> being the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of it; we may ſuppoſe, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100460:16"/>as he <hi>feared God,</hi> and all his Houſe, ſo he <hi>prayed</hi> with all his Houſe unto God. And he himſelf ſeems ſo to explain it, <hi>I prayed to God in mine Houſe at the ninth Hour;</hi> or with <hi>my Houſhold,</hi> as it may be rendered. He afterwards called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether his Kindred, and his near Friends, when <hi>Peter</hi> came; but mentions not the calling of his Houſhold, as what was uſual and ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>And the praying <hi>always,</hi> or <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> can hardly bear a leſs Senſe, than the doing of it every Day: As the <hi>daily Sacrifice</hi> which God appointed the Jews, is called <hi>the continual Sacrifice,</hi> which was offered Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.11. So <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> is ſaid to eat Bread at the King's Table <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.7. that is, at Meal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time every Day. Nature and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture both ſeem to concur to recommend <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening</hi> as the proper Seaſon for Prayer. <hi>It is good to give Thanks unto the Lord, and to ſing Praiſes to thy Name, O moſt High; to ſhew forth thy Loving-kindneſs every Morning, and thy Faithfulneſs every Night.</hi> Pſ. 92.1, 2. God is to be worſhiped by all Perſons, and all People, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.27, 28. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 66.4. and by Social Worſhip, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34.3.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100460:16"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 12.12. The general Nature of Worſhip, and all the Eſſentials of true Divine Worſhip is found in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God by <hi>Families, as ſuch.</hi> The Object, the End, and the Rule is the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ſince there are many Commands in Scripture concerning Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and this part of it, <hi>Prayer</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, which are of general Extent, ſuch as of praying <hi>always,</hi> and giving thanks <hi>always,</hi> and <hi>continuing in Prayer and Thankſgivings with all Prayer and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in the Spirit, every where lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up holy hands, in every thing giving thanks,</hi> &amp;c. 'twill be hard to obey all theſe Commands, and yet live in the neglect of Family-Prayer. For by the Light of Nature we may from hence be able to determine the Performance of this Duty, to be <hi>every Day,</hi> as a proper Time, and in <hi>every Houſe,</hi> as a proper Place for it. But if it were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permitted us, we are greatly want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our own Intereſt to neglect it. Theſe general Rules and Precepts do <hi>at leaſt</hi> warrant, and make lawful our <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together</hi> every Day. We have leave to pray together, and ſhall we not uſe it? What if God ſhould have forbidden
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100460:17"/>us; if he ſhould put any of our Families under an <hi>Interdict;</hi> and ſay, You ſhall not pray to me: I will not receive a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from you. Your Neighbours may pray to me every Morning and Night, I'll hear them, and accept them. As for you, you ſhall have no Family-Altar, or Sacrifice. Who would not be griev'd to be forbidden ſuch a daily Privilege? Who would not then uſe it, if they might? And becauſe the Evening and Morning do make one Day, as the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and the End do comprehend the whole; he that prays every <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening,</hi> may be ſaid to pray <hi>continually,</hi> to pray <hi>always,</hi> to pray <hi>without ceaſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not the Light of Nature, which inſtructs us in the Being of God, and the Immortality of the Soul, oblige us to endeavour the good of thoſe in our Families? And as one proper means of their ſpiritual Welfare, it may direct the Maſter of a Family to pray with them; there being <hi>Family-Sins</hi> to be confeſſed by us, and forgiven by God; there being many <hi>Temptations</hi> every day to be reſiſted, <hi>Wants</hi> to be ſupplied, <hi>Duties</hi> performed, <hi>Graces</hi> exerciſed, <hi>Croſſes</hi> prevented, <hi>Mercies</hi> acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>&amp;c. in Families, as ſuch:</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100460:17"/>unto all theſe, Family-Prayer and Worſhip is an excellent Means.</p>
            <p>Some of thoſe who had not the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Scripture-Revelation, have yet had <hi>their Houſhold-Gods.</hi> The Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Nations had their <hi>Teraphim;</hi> the <hi>Egyptians, Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> had their <hi>Lares</hi> and <hi>Penates,</hi> a Sort of Family-Gods, to rule, preſerve, and defend them in their Houſes; whom they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped and ſacrificed unto in their Houſes: and ſeveral of them had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Room, ſet a-part for an <hi>Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to that purpoſe. The Heathen Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, <hi>Heſiod, Homer,</hi> and others, mention their <hi>daily Sacrifices</hi> to their Gods <hi>every Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening;</hi> that they might proſper, and ſucceed by their Favour in all their Affairs: and their Practice may be urged for our <hi>Conviction.</hi> It ſeems a Preſcription of the Law of Nature, that every Society wherein Men do unite, and joyn according to the Mind of God, ſhould own their Dependance on him, by ſome Worſhip common to that Society; and as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the Name of it; eſpecially is it ſo, as to <hi>an Houſhold</hi> or <hi>Family,</hi> which is the Foundation of all other Societies. Hence there were Sacrifices
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100460:18"/>peculiar unto <hi>Families</hi> before the Law, wherein the Father of the Family was the ſacred Adminiſtrator. So <hi>Job</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd Burnt-Offerings for himſelf and Family, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.5. and <hi>Jacob</hi> for his, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35. And ſuch Family-Sacrifices were famous among the
<note n="*" place="bottom">An Eminent Inſtance hereof the <hi>Roman Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> gives us in <hi>C. Fabius,</hi> who when <hi>Rome</hi> was ſack'd by the <hi>Gauls,</hi> and the Capitol beſieged, upon the ſtated Time of the ſolemn Worſhip and Sacrifices of the Family of the <hi>Fabii,</hi> paſſed through the Enemies Camp to the <hi>Quirinal</hi> Hill, and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god the accuſtomed <hi>Sacra,</hi> returning to the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol,</hi> without Diſturbance or Affront from the Enemy. <hi>Liv.</hi> lib. 5. And the Family-Ceremonies in the Sacrifice of an Oxe unto <hi>Hercales,</hi> by the <hi>Folitii</hi> and <hi>Pinarii,</hi> were adopted by <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Numa,</hi> into the uſe of the whole People, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of thoſe Families being made as it were their. <hi>Publick Prirſts</hi> thereby. And after they had confirm'd the Adminiſtration of their <hi>Sura</hi> in publick Solemnities for the whole Community, yet they left it free to <hi>ſingle Parſons</hi> and <hi>Families,</hi> to ſacrifice for themſelves as they ſaw good. For as they took up the <hi>Former</hi> Courſe, probably from the Form and Example of <hi>Moſaical</hi> Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo they did the <hi>Latt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from the Original Practice and Tradition of the World. Even the meaneſt of the People continued their Family-<hi>Libations. Sacrima</hi> they called the Wine which your Countrymen offered to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> as <hi>Feſtus</hi> teſtifies; and <hi>Capar,</hi> the Veſſel out of which they drew the Wine, whereof they made a <hi>Libation</hi> to <hi>Jupiter. Struſerta</hi> and <hi>Suo-veturaulia,</hi> were the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifices of poor Families. And ſomething in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of this Original Practice, continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People of God, after the giving of the law. — Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> on the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Vol. 2. Exer. cit. 10. §. 4.</note> Heathens.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100460:18"/>And ſhall the Pagans out-do us? Shall they be ſenſible of their Dependance in their Families on ſome Superiour Aids, ſo as to worſhip Stocks and Stones in their Houſes, rather than have no Worſhip at all; and ſhall Chriſtians live contentedly without the Worſhip of the true God in their Families? <hi>All People will walk every one in the Name of bis God,</hi> and ſhall not <hi>We</hi> reſolve <hi>to walk in the Name of the Lord our God for ever?</hi> Mic. 4.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN SHORT,</hi> If God be the Founder, the Owner, the Governour and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour of <hi>Families;</hi> If ſuch little Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be of his <hi>Appointment,</hi> and do both need and receive daily <hi>Mercies</hi> from him; it is but fit he ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped, and owned every Day in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Families. Before the giving of the Law to <hi>Moſes,</hi> how was God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100460:19"/>but in Families? Family-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was the firſt kind of Social Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: Religion was at firſt confin'd to ſingle Perſons; upon the Increaſe of Mankind it begun in Families. Every Ruler of a Family was then a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to his own Houſe, or offered his own Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and governed his <hi>Family,</hi> not only as <hi>ſuch,</hi> but as a Religious Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Afterwards Religion ſpread into larger Societies. This was the firſt Power God intruſted Man with, to be the Head, and Ruler, and Father of a Family; to take care of the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of that little Society, and of all that belonged to it: Eſpecially to take care of Religion, and the Worſhip of God there. He was not only the Civil Governour, but the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> though not by proper <hi>Office,</hi> for that reſults not from the Light and Law of Nature, but depends on Inſtitution, as <hi>ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical,</hi> and repreſentative of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt. I mention this, becauſe it is commonly ſaid, that the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the <hi>Firſtborn,</hi> as a Branch of the <hi>Primogeniture;</hi> and that the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of every Family was in the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Firſtborn, till the time of the Levitical Law. But this is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100460:19"/>not
<note n="*" place="bottom">Bp <hi>Stilling fleet</hi>'s Irenicum, Part I. Chap. 4. ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Theodoret.</hi> queſt. 108. in <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Iſid. Peluſ.</hi> lib. 2. Ep. 47, &amp; 48.</note> proved from Scripture; what is commonly alledged from <hi>Numb.</hi> 3.41. of the <hi>Levites</hi> being taken inſtead of the <hi>Firſtborn,</hi> will conclude no ſuch thing. God having delivered their Firſtborn in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 12.23. called for them to be ſanctiſied to him, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.22. upon the Account of the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Propriety he had in them by that Deliverance; and not on the Account of any ſpecial Service, for many were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for that by reaſon of Age: and which is obſervable, God requires as well the Firſtborn of <hi>Beaſts</hi> to be ſanctified, and redeemed. When therefore God would ſettle a way of Worſhip, he gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> liberty to redeem them, and inſtead of the Firſtborn, he pitched on the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> for his own Service.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we find in Scripture, that the Younger were ordinarily preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Firſtborn, as <hi>Abel</hi> before <hi>Cain, Seth</hi> before <hi>Japheth, Abraham</hi> before his Elder Brethren, <hi>Iſaac</hi> before <hi>Iſhmael, Jacob</hi> before <hi>Eſau, Judah</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100460:20"/>
               <hi>Reuben, Ephraim</hi> before <hi>Manaſſes, Moſes</hi> before <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> before the reſt of his Brethren, although that was after the Law. From the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doubtleſs the Father of the Family was the High-Prieſt to it, and the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſacrificing was committed to him, and herein it is
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> on the <hi>Hebr.</hi> vol. 2. exercir. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, §. 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> probable he had the ſpecial Aſſiſtance of the Firſtborn of the Family, whereby he might be initiated into his future Duty. But that Office of a Prieſt was not confin'd to the Elder Brother, for <hi>Abel</hi> offered Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in his own Perſon, while his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his Elder Brother were alive, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did after the Flood, while the Eldeſt Son of <hi>Noah</hi> was living; and when the Younger Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> were ſeparated, and diſpers'd into ſeveral diſtinct Families, they did not loſe the Right of ſolemnizing the Worſhip of God thereby.</p>
            <p>When the World increaſed, and lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Societies were ſet up, the Power of a Parent as Head of a Family was in ſome reſpects broken, and Parents had not the Power of Life and Death over
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100460:20"/>their Children, as before: But much of the Power of a Parent, and Maſter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his own Family, is continued by God; and therefore Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are commanded to obey their Parents and Maſters, as well as to obey Civil Magiſtrates. Now I would ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue thus, That if <hi>Family-Worſhip,</hi> at firſt, did not exclude <hi>perſonal</hi> Religion, and private Prayer to God by one alone, as doubtleſs it did not; then the publick Worſhip of God (when many Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies meet together) ſhould not exclude Family-Worſhip, or the daily Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God in particular Families, by as many of ſuch a little Society as can come together. There is the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>Family-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> ſhould continue, after the <hi>publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of God by many Families together is ſet up, as that <hi>Perſonal Religion,</hi> and ſecret <hi>Prayer</hi> ſhould continue a Duty, after God began to be worſhip'd in <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon Queen <hi>Heſter</hi>'s keeping a Faſt with her Maids, which was extraordinary; nor, enlarge on the Example of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who built an Altar, and called on the Name of the Lord, and called on his Family to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100460:21"/>for it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2, 3. <hi>Saying to his Houſhold, and all that were with him, Put away the ſtrange Gods, and let us build an Altar to Jehovah,</hi> &amp;c. His Grandfather <hi>Abraham</hi> circumciſed all the Males in his Houſe, brought 'em under the Bond and Seal of the Covenant; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he reſided with his Family for any conſiderable time, he built Altars, and offered Sacrifices. That dreadful Curſe imprecated (or denounced rather, and predicted) upon <hi>the Families that call not upon God's Name,</hi> (though princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally meaning <hi>Tribes of People;</hi> and by calling on the Name of God, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true God in oppoſition to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry;) yet deſerves to be conſidered, becauſe by parity of Reaſon, it may extend to the <hi>leſſer Societies,</hi> where the True God is not owned, and worſhiped.</p>
            <p>God has alſo promiſed to bleſs the Habitations of the Juſt, and he has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten owned by his Providence his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of Family-Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. When all the Old World had neglected God, and corrupted their Ways, the true Religion continued but in the Family of <hi>Noah;</hi> He and his were ſaved from the Univerſal Deluge, when the reſt were ſwept away by the Flood.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100460:21"/>
            <p>Agreeable to this is a Paſſage, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently mentioned to this purpoſe, <hi>in Suitzerland</hi> in the <hi>Canton</hi> of <hi>Bern, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Chriſti</hi> 1584, when a whole Village, conſiſting of <hi>ninety</hi> Houſes, were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by an <hi>Earth-quake;</hi> there was but one Family excepted, and but one half Houſe preſerved; and in that half of the Houſe that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the Maſter of the Family was earneſtly praying to God, with his Wife and Children, while the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake deſtroyed all his Neighbours.</p>
            <p>For the Inſtruction and Teaching of Children and Servants, as a part of Family-Religion, there are ſufficiently expreſs Scriptures. <hi>To bring them up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord; To train them up in the way wherein they ſhould go;</hi> And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to teach them <hi>to pray</hi> to God, and praiſe him. And the Example of a Parent or Maſter is one of the beſt ways of <hi>teaching</hi> them. The Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. That he that doth not provide for his own Houſe and Family, <hi>hath denied the Faith,</hi> and <hi>is worſe than an Infidel.</hi> He that doth not <hi>provide Food</hi> and <hi>Raiment</hi> for thoſe of his own Houſhold, comes under this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100460:22"/>Character. And if he be ſo bad, who takes no care of the Welfare of their Bodies, what ſhall we think of him who has no Concern for their Souls; not to inſtruct them in their Duty to God, not to pray with them, not to read the Holy Scriptures to them? He, it may be, feeds and clothes his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants, as a kind Father and Maſter, and as an <hi>Engliſh-Man,</hi> but carries it to their Souls like a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>Indian,</hi> or a Careleſs Inſidel. As much more worth as the Soul is than the Body, ſo much worſe is that Man that is careleſs of the Souls in his Family, than he that is careleſs of their Bodies: Such a one the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>has denied the Faith,</hi> he cannot with any Face pretend to be <hi>a Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſhameful then is it, for Men to be admitted to the higheſt Privileges of Chriſtians, I mean to <hi>the Table of the Lord,</hi> and yet neglect the Worſhip of God in their Families? We find in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.47, 48. that no Proſelyte might preſume to come to the Paſſover, unleſs <hi>his whole Houſe,</hi> as well as himſelf, were <hi>circumciſed,</hi> and profeſſed the Jewiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If this Law, as well as its Equ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, were ſtill in force, how few would
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100460:22"/>now come to the holy Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that doth not provide for his own, is worſe than an Infidel.</hi> He that would ſuffer their Bodies to ſtarve, and does not give them ſufficient proper Food, deſerves this Cenſure and Reproach: much more doth he who neglects their Souls. It is not indifferent to you, whether your Children and Servants be ſed, and clothed, and have neceſſary Proviſions, or no; whether they be nouriſhed, or whether they be ſtarved: And is it nothing to you whether they be ſaved or damned? You would not be acceſſory to the Murder of their Bodies, and will you not be as careful to avoid the like, and greater Guilt with reference to their Souls?</p>
            <p>If Parents had no Truſt and Charge commited to them from God (who ſaith, <hi>All Souls are mine</hi>) with relation to the Souls of their Children; if Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ers were to give no Account to God of their Servants, but whether they gave them Food and Wages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they might be concerned as to theſe things. But you are Stewards intruſted with the Care of their Souls, as well as their Bodies. And it will be ſad hereafter, for a Child to ſay before the Bar of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100460:23"/>Chriſt, There ſtands my cruel Father or Mother, who never prayed with me, or inſtructed me in the Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſo I minded it not. The like for a Servant; he lived ſo many Years with ſuch or ſuch a Maſter, and never had any Aſſiſtance from him to further his Salvation.</p>
            <p>Certainly as to Children, <hi>Parents</hi> are more eſpecially obliged, as having greater and nearer Obligations to them, than any Miniſters or Paſtors can have to their People. Your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are Parts of your ſelves, and if you are not concerned for their Souls, you are unnatural and cruel to them: It is from you, their immediate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, that they receive their corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nature, their Pollution and Miſery; and therefore you are bound to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour their Recovery and Cure. You will alſo condemn your ſelves, in being ſollicitous for their Bodily Welfare (which moſt are to an exceſs) while you neglect the Salvation of their Souls. And by your Care of their Souls, you provide for their Bodily Welfare too. God hath promiſed to bleſs the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Servants. Tho the Church was continued in the Line of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100460:23"/>God promiſed to bleſs <hi>Iſhmael</hi> for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake of his Father <hi>Abraham. I will make him a great Nation, for he is thy Seed;</hi> Gen. 21.13. But remember they muſt die, and they are capable of Grace and Immortality; and will you only provide for them as you do for your Beaſts? <hi>Plutarch</hi> taxing the Abuſe of Parents, who ſtrive to leave their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Rich, and not Vertuous, ſaith, they do like thoſe who are ſollicitous about the Shoe, but neglect the Foot. They depend on you for their Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Livelihood, and ſo you have an Advantage to promote their Good; they will hearken to your Counſels, when they will not regard what a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter can ſay. You have an Intereſt in their Affections, joyn'd with an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over them; they are with you in their tender Years, and ſo your Work is the eaſier.</p>
            <p>This is well deſcribed by an eloquent
<note n="*" place="bottom">Biſhop <hi>Jer. Taylor</hi>'s Diſcourſe of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">•.</hi> 1653. p. 54, 55.</note> Pen. <q>God was confident concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he would teach his Children; and Parents have great Power by ſtrict Education, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100460:24"/>Diſcipline, to form the Minds of Children to Vertue. <hi>Joſhua</hi> did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for his Houſhold, <hi>I and my Houſe will ſerve the Lord;</hi> and for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren we may better do it, becauſe till they are of perfect Choice, no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the World is ſo great, as that of Parents over their Children. They rule over their Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Children know nothing but what they are told, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it infinitely: And it is a rare Art of the Spirit to engage <hi>Parents</hi> to bring them up well <hi>in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord.</hi> They are Perſons obliged by a ſuperinduced Band; they are to give them In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and holy Principles, as they give them Meat. It is certain Parents may better ſtipulate for their Children, than the Church can for Men or Women. They may be Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, and the next day may change their Reſolution, and grow weary of their Vow; and that is the moſt that Children can do when they come of Age; and it is much in the Parents whether the Children ſhall do any ſuch thing or no —. For Education can introduce a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100460:24"/>and a kind of ſecond Nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which Children cannot kick, unleſs they do ſome Violence to themſelves, and their Inclinations. And altho it fails too often, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it fails, yet we pronounce pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently concerning future things, when we have a leſs Influence into the Event, than in the preſent Caſe.</q> This would ſucceed oftner, if Parents were faithful in their Duty to them while young. It would commonly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed if you begun betimes, according to the Compariſon which one makes of Childhood and Youth, to Water ſpilt on a Table, it rune after you that way which you draw your Finger. They may be prejudiced againſt a holy Life, or ſettled in a way of Sin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are capable of profiting by publick preaching: But your teaching them at home, as it may begin ſooner, ſo will prevail more: and they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg your Teaching to be with <hi>more Authority</hi> than ours. I fear, ſaith a great
<note n="*" place="bottom">See more largely, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Saints Reſt, Part 3. Chap. 14. Sect. 11.</note> Divine, that many of thoſe, who are otherwiſe good People, do
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100460:25"/>little underſtand, or conſider the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which their Teachers have over them from Chriſt. They know, it may be, to value their <hi>Gifts,</hi> but think not themſelves bound to learn of them, and obey them in the Lord, by virtue of their <hi>Office.</hi> However, the Obligation of Miniſters to teach you and your Children, will not can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel your Duty of Teaching them at home; no more than that becauſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates muſt govern you and your Children, you ſhould therefore not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern your own Families.</p>
            <p>How many yet miſimprove all theſe Advantages, to do the Devil's Work, and teach their Children the way to Hell, by inducing them to ſin betimes; by inſtructing them to be proud and revengeful, to backbite and rail, to ſpeak filthily, to curſe and ſwear, to ſcorn Holineſs, and the Word, and Miniſters, and Ways of God. How much worſe, <hi>ſays one,</hi> are <hi>ſuch Parents</hi> than <hi>the Devil</hi> himſelf! As it is worſe for a Mother to daſh out the Brains of her own Child againſt a Wall, than for a Wolf, or a Dog, or a Bear to kill her Child. It is in your Hands to do them the greateſt Kindneſs, or Cruelty
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100460:25"/>in all the World: And if you ſaw a Burning Furnace, much more the Flames of Hell; what would you think of that Parent, who could find in his heart, to caſt the Child into it, or to put him into the hands of one that would?</p>
            <p>If therefore you love them, ſhew it in thoſe things wherein their greateſt Intereſt is concerned. Do not ſay you love them, and yet be ſo unmerciful as to damn them: And what can you poſſibly do more to damn them, than to bring them up in Ignorance, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, and neglect of God? The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil damns none but by tempting to Sin, and drawing them from Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for there is no other way to Hell. But it is no great wonder; for you do by <hi>Your Children,</hi> but as you do by <hi>Your Selves:</hi> You ſay, you deſire not to damn your ſelves, but yet you do it: So it is with reſpect to them. Shall he that caſts his Child into the Sea, ſay he intends not to drown him? Or he that ſends him into a Peſt-houſe, or a Stews, ſay he intends not to indanger his Health? Or that trains him up in Thievery, and Robbing, ſay that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to have him hanged? It is all one in effect; for the Law determins
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100460:26"/>it, and the Judge will take care to have it done.</p>
            <p>As ever you would not be charged by God with the Murder of their Souls, and have them cry out againſt you in everlaſting Fire, as the Means of their Ruine, be now faithful and diligent for their Salvation. It will be ſad for thoſe, who dedicated their Children to God by Baptiſm in their Infancy, that afterwards they ſhould bring them up for the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh; as God complains, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Thou haſt taken thy Sons, and thy Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which thou haſt born <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTO ME, and theſe thou haſt ſacrificed to be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> That Sin in the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their Sons and their Daughters to Devils, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.37. was leſs than that of Negligent and Prophane Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who ſacrifice not only the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but the Souls of their Children to Satan, and ſo bring them forth to the <hi>Murderer,</hi> Hoſ. 9.13.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole, I hope I have ſaid enough to recommend and urge the Duty, till I hear what is further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, beſides the want of expreſs po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Scripture. Some of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100460:26"/>Objections, I ſhall conſider in the next Letter. Let Conſcience be faithful, and if you admit of Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by what you have read, take heed how you ſtifle it, or delay to do that, which you cannot deny but you ought to do.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:100460:27"/>
            <head>Of Family Religion.</head>
            <head type="sub">The SECOND LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am ſenſible that a great deal more might be ſaid, and more <hi>Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> to prove and urge ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a Duty, as <hi>Family Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> than what I have mentioned in the former Letter. What is done in the midſt of many Interruptions, now a little, and then a little, cannot be expected ſhould have that Beauty, Order, and Exactneſs of Method and Connexion, which you may think neceſſary. However, I proceed to what I promiſed, in anſwer to ſome Objections: Only let me premiſe, that it is foretold concerning the days of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> when the Spirit of Grace and Supplication ſhall be poured out on the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and on the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100460:27"/>of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> when the Multitude of the Iſles ſhall rejoyce, and all Fleſh ſhall ſee the Glory of the Lord; That <hi>Holineſs to the Lord,</hi> (which was the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription on the Mitre of the <hi>High Priest</hi>) <hi>ſhall be upon the very Bells of the Horſes, and the Pots in the Lord's Houſe,</hi> or the Ordinary Pots in the Kitchins of the Temple, <hi>ſhall be like the Bowls before the Altar,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. chap. 14.20, 21.</note> which received the Blood of the Sacrifices; Yea <hi>every Pot in</hi> Judah, <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſhall be Holineſs unto the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> That is, the Utenſils of <hi>Private Houſes</hi> ſhall be dedicated to God, every <hi>Family</hi> ſhall be a <hi>Temple,</hi> wherein God ſhall be worſhiped.</p>
            <p>And as God required of the <hi>Jews</hi> a <hi>Continual Burnt-Offering,</hi> or a daily Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of two Lambs; the one in the <hi>Morning,</hi> the other in the <hi>Evening:</hi> It may be expected that ſo often (at leaſt) he ſhould be worſhiped every Day in the Families of his People. Our daily Sacrifices, by Prayer and Praiſe, under the fuller Diſpenſation of Goſpel-Grace, ſhould not be fewer or leſs frequent than theirs of another ſort.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100460:28"/>
            <p>But I hope I have ſaid enough in the <hi>Former Letter</hi> to recommend the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in Families; Doubtleſs one Advantage of it would be, to ſit us for thoſe other <hi>Duties,</hi> and Parts of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which are ſometimes urged to excuſe the Neglect of <hi>this.</hi> For how many are ready to ſay, we pray to God every day in <hi>Secret,</hi> and we joyn every Week with others in <hi>Publick Worſhip;</hi> and what need of any more? Whereas one part of our Duty is ſo far from interfering with the other, that the one will help to the better performance of the other. By pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Secret,</hi> you will be inabled to pray in your <hi>Family:</hi> and by both theſe may obtain Aſſiſtance and Succeſs in the <hi>Publick Worſhip</hi> of God; and by at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon the Publick Worſhip, you will be fitted for the other parts of your Duty in Secret and Private. You are obliged to pray in Secret, if you had no Families; and it is very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in a numerous Family, whether all the Members of it do daily pray in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, or not.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that there are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe who make a great Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, who yet live in the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100460:28"/>neglect of Family Worſhip; I anſwer, that is no wonder, becauſe there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who profeſs to be what they are not; who have a Name to live, and are dead. But if they be real, upright Chriſtians, they are either under the Power of a preſent Temptation, or under the Conduct of an erring Mind, as miſled by ſome Falſe Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo they will neglect this Duty no longer, than till their Errour be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; or the preſent Difficulties in the way of this Practice are got over; which many ſay they would be glad of, but cannot yet attain.</p>
            <p>As in ſome Families it is pretended they have not <hi>Time</hi> every day for ſuch Work: My Trade will not allow me, I have a Charge of Children that muſt be maintained, and my Buſineſs muſt be minded; or I am obliged to be Abroad early and late; I cannot read the Holy Scriptures in my Family, and pray every day with thoſe of the Family, for <hi>want of Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have often thought of this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Winter, and how the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God has removed it, as to a great many Families, to their ſad Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment and Sorrow. What elſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100460:29"/>mean the many Complaints of Starving Families, for <hi>want of Trade?</hi> They have Time enough now to pray, for they have no Work. Let ſuch reflect upon themſelves, and conſider how righteous it is from God, that whereas, while they had Trade and Buſineſs, they would not find <hi>Time</hi> to pray, God ſhould puniſh their Neglect by blaſting their Endeavours; and now they want <hi>Trade,</hi> and would be glad of Work to employ their <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what need is there for any to be ſo long in Family-Worſhip, as to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Buſineſs of their particular Calling? Though it may be, all in the Family cannot come together, yet ſome may, and poſſibly the greater part, if a little Prudence, and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be uſed, as to the choice of the Time.</p>
            <p>And if leſs time were ſpent in the <hi>Morning,</hi> in moſt caſes there might be more redeemed in the <hi>Evening.</hi> Many might redeem time from the <hi>Coffee-Houſe,</hi> and from the <hi>Tavern,</hi> and from time-waſting <hi>Clubs,</hi> and Meetings by appointment, without Buſineſs; while their Children and Servants at home are expoſed to Temptation, and the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100460:29"/>Worſhip of God neglected there, or hudled over ſlightly, towards midnight, between ſleeping and waking.</p>
            <p>Every one will grant, that Succeſs in his Trade and Calling depends upon the Bleſſing of Heaven; but moſt live as if they believed nothing of it. For it can hardly be denied, that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Day with God, and heartily implore his <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> is the beſt way to have it. If what you get be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the Divine Bleſſing, you will have little Comfort in ſuch increaſe. And how can it be proved, that it is your Duty to graſp ſo much Worldly Buſineſs, as is inconſiſtent with the worſhiping of God in your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and having time to mind the Souls of thoſe committed to your Charge? <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> you ſay, <hi>muſt be minded.</hi> Your lawful proper Buſineſs, it is true, muſt be ſo, in its place: But, as one ſays, <hi>this Devil of (pretended) Buſineſs, has deſtroyed and damned more Souls, than all the Devils in Hell beſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How eaſily can God, by Sickneſs, or grievous Pains, unfit you for the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Calling, or diſable your Servants by Sickneſs, if he be provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by your neglect of him in your
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100460:30"/>Families? He may either blaſt all your Diligence; the Curſe of God ſhall blow upon you; you ſhall labour much and get nothing. Or he may diſable you and yours from following your Trade and Buſineſs. O how eaſily can God make you know, that if you will not find a time to pray, you muſt have a time to be ſick, as well as others! How ſoon, and ſuddenly may he ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon you by Death to his Judgment-Seat! Think now, whether, when you ſhall appear there, you will pretend the want of time for this Work. Let Conſcience ſpeak the Truth; Is it not that you want a Heart? God allows us a ſufficient <hi>Time</hi> for our particular Calling. If our Hearts were filled with Love to God, and awed with his Holy Fear, we ſhould not rob him of that which belongs to his Service. The Grace of God to ſanctify our Hearts, would anſwer and remove a thouſand ſuch Pretences.</p>
            <p>There be many, who cannot plead the want of Leaſure, who pretend the want of <hi>Parts,</hi> and <hi>Gifts</hi> to inſtruct and teach others, or to pray with them. But let them ſeriouſly accuſtom them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſecret Prayer, and they may
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100460:30"/>quickly learn to pray in their Families. Get but your Hearts affected in a due manner with Family Wants, and Sins, and Mercies; and you will ſoon be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out of the abundance of the Heart, to expreſs your ſelves ſufficiently well: For it is not fine Words, and good Language that God regards, and is pleaſed with, but a ſerious, reverend, holy, thankful Heart. You do not want words to expreſs your Deſires in other Caſes; nor would you here, if you were to beg your own Life, or that of a dear Relation, of an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly King or Judge. It is a ſhame for Chriſtians, who have lived long under the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, and have ſuch Advantages of the Bible in a known Tongue, and of ſo many uſeful practical Books, to pretend the want of Gifts for this Duty. However, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe a <hi>Form,</hi> and take the Aſſiſtance of a Book for a while, than wholly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Duty. Almoſt all the Old Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (called <hi>Puritans</hi>) acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lawfulneſs of a <hi>Form of Prayer,</hi> and adviſed the uſe of one in this Caſe. It is better to own and acknowledge God, and do ſomething in this kind, though with ſome Imperfection, than
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100460:31"/>affront him, and deſpiſe him, by a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal neglect. And for ſome Maſters of Families, (I know not, all Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces conſidered, but) the uſe of a good Form, may be more adviſable, and more for the good of thoſe with whom they joyn, than to pray without <hi>One.</hi> All things ſhould be done for <hi>Edifiea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and for thoſe to uſe a Form, who cannot otherwiſe do ſo well, is for Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: And Experience will prove that ſome cannot do ſo well without one.</p>
            <p>I deny not, but the Spirit of Grace is a Spirit of Supplication, and ready to aſſiſt and enable us in ſome meaſure to pray: ſo that if you neglect not the Gift that is in you, you would increaſe in this, and other Gifts by Exerciſe. The Holy Scriptures will furniſh you with Matter and Expreſſions; and if you ſtudy your own Hearts, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſtate of your Family, you will be competontly able to apply them: And God will afford you that Aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit which is needful. As in the Caſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he excuſes himſelf from ſpeaking to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah,</hi> as God would have him, becauſe he was not cloquent, but <hi>ſlow of ſpeech.</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:100460:31"/>The Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 4.11. <hi>Who veaketh the Dumb to ſpeak? Who hath made Man's Mouth? Have not I the Lord? Now therefore go, and I will be with thy Mouth, teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</hi> His <hi>Call</hi> to ſpeak to <hi>Pharach</hi> was <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> and ſo was his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Aſſiſtance from God. Yours to Family Prayer is <hi>Ordinary;</hi> and the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Help, and Aſſiſtance</hi> you therein need, you may likewiſe expect.</p>
            <p>It is a greater Diſconragement to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the daily Worſhip of God in their <hi>Families,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> are often compoſed of ſuch Perſons, as care not to joyn in ſuch Duties: Or they are ſuch Scoffers, that it is a ſcruple whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould be ſuffered to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, if they were willing. Some had rather pray alone, than indeavour, or deſire ſuch Company; they think they had better leave them out, than have their preſence, who will not heartily joyn in the Requeſts that are made to God, and who deſire not his Grace, or ſeek his Favour.</p>
            <p>To ſuch it may be ſaid, That it is the Duty even of wicked Men to pray to God: and you know not what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs their joyning with you may be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100460:32"/>attended with. Some have dated their firſt Conviction and Converſion, from <hi>Family Prayer</hi> and <hi>Inſtruction.</hi> You knowing the Sins of thoſe in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, ſhould be very ſerious in the Confeſſion of Sin; and God may touch their Hearts, and give them Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. However, if you look to your own Hearts, and do not regard Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there, the Wickedneſs of others in the Family ſhall not be laid to your Charge, while you do what lies in you for their Recovery. The Preſence of <hi>Judas</hi> with our Lord and Saviour, when he prayed with his Diſciples, did not render them unacceptable to God: For <hi>I know,</hi> ſays <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Father, <hi>thou heareſt me always.</hi> If you are ſincere in your Worſhip, the Preſence of unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons will not obſtruct your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God. Another Man's Unbelief will not prejudice thy Faith. If you ſhould ſcruple to pray in your Families on that account; What think you of a Miniſter's Prayer in the Publick Congregation? If any neglect Family Worſhip on this Pretence, they are moſt likely to be ſuch, as refuſe to come to the Lord's Table, becauſe of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſuppoſed unworthy. Perſons,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100460:32"/>But how is it that they come to hear the Word, and join in publick Prayer in the Congregation, while this Objection is ſtronger there, than with reference to Prayer in their own Houſes?</p>
            <p>The Authority of Parents as to their Children is ſo manifeſt, and their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to oblige them to join in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God is ſo plain; that it is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally as to ſcornful, or ſtubborn <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> that this Objection ſpeaks. And as to them, unleſs they prove much otherwiſe than you thought they would, you were greatly to blame in admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch: And after trial of other Means for their Conviction and Cure, if they can be removed, you ought to do it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.4, 5, 7. <hi>A froward Heart ſhall depart from me, a Slanderer will I cut off; He that telleth Lies ſhall not tarry in my ſight,</hi> or dwell in my Houſe. But where is the Authority of the Head of a Family all this while? Should they not obſerve your Orders in Matters of Trade and Buſineſs, you would quickly let them know you were their Maſters. And does that Relation ſignify nothing to them, while they dwell under your Roof, and are imployed in your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? Doth not the Fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100460:33"/>ſuppoſe a Maſter's Authority to bring his Family to worſhip God with him? And your Concern for their Souls chligeth you to endeavour it.</p>
            <p>There is one very common Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that I fear, has too much of ſad Truth for the Foundation of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That many of thoſe, who pray in their Families, and read the Holy Scriptures there, and keep up the Externals of Religion beyond their Neighbours, do yet live no better, than ſuch as pray not; their Children are no better than other Mens Children; their Servants are no better than other Mens Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; they themſelves no better than their prayerleſs Neighbours: They are one thing on their Knees, and another on their Feet. They are as vain and worldly, as proud and paſſionate, as hard to the Poor, as falſe in their Dealings, as revengeful and inexorable, as others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would to God there were no ground for this Objection. Wo be to the World becauſe of ſuch Offences, but wo be to them by whom they come. Who can tell what unſpeakable Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief ſuch do, who keep up the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in their Families, and yet
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100460:33"/>walk diſorderly in their daily Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations? Who begin with God in the Morning, and keep Company with the Devil all the Day after. What Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks do they lay in the way of ignorant Children, and ungodly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Neighbours, who are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it? They tempt them to be <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and deny God, and make them queſtion the Reality of Religion. But whatever Hypocriſie any ſuch may be guilty of in ſuch like Duties, it will not diſcharge you from the Obligation to perform them ſincerely. You may as well refuſe to join in publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, becauſe ſome conſtant Hearers are no better than ſome of thoſe who ſtay away, and turn their Backs upon all ſuch poſitive Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p>However, it is not the Fruit of their praying, but the want of Seriouſneſs and Sincerity, which provokes God to leave them to the Power of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is not long of Chriſt, and of the Holy Scriptures, and of Religion, and of Chriſtianity, that any profeſſing Chriſtians are ſo bad. No Ruler was ever ſo ſevere againſt Sin, as Jeſus Chriſt; no Law was ever ſo ſtrict in the forbidding Sin, as the Laws of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100460:34"/>Chriſt: The Rule is ſtreight, and the Chriſtian Religion is not to be blamed, becauſe ſome that profeſs it are not true to their own Profeſſion: They condemn themſelves, and diſhonour God, and reproach their Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and without Repentance he will condemn them too; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.17. <hi>Theſe things baſt thou done, and I kept ſilence; thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf; but I will reprove thee, and ſet thy Sins in order before thee.</hi> I will reject your Sacrifices, I will ſpread the Dung of your ſolemn Services be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Face; Your very Prayers ſhall witneſs againſt you.</p>
            <p>A Caution yet is needful here, To take heed of bearing falſe Witneſs, or eaſily believing one againſt our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Do not haſtily credit every Story you are told, againſt ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Religion. For the Devil imploys a great many to do his Work, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming and diſcrediting ſuch. Every leſſer Fall of ſuch a one ſhall be blazon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Though it were but a ſingle Fault, committed but once, and ſoon and heartily repented of, and ſeldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver relapſed into; it ſhall yet be longer talk'd of, and more aggravated, than
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100460:34"/>the cuſtomary, continued, foul Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of others. This is ſeen daily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch, whoſe Hearts are filled with Enmity againſt real Holineſs.</p>
            <p>Granting therefore, (what is too no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious to be denied) that <hi>ſome</hi> Few, who pray to <hi>God</hi> every Day, do yet live as if they believed there were <hi>none;</hi> yet compare the Families of ſuch as daily worſhip God together, with the Families of others, that neglect God and Religion; and it is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily true, that the <hi>former</hi> are no better than the <hi>latter:</hi> The Families of ſuch are commonly the Nurſeries of Religion. Was not <hi>Noah</hi>'s Family bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the drowned World, though there were one <hi>Cham</hi> in it? as there was one <hi>Judas</hi> in the Family of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Himſelf? What would you think of a Man, ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who, looking over his Neighbour's Garden, when his own is all over-run with Weeds, and wholly neglected, ſhould ſee in his Neighbour's Ground here and there a Weed, mixt with much better Stuff; and thereupon ſhould ſay, Theſe Men that beſtow ſo much Pains about their Gardens, in dunging and weeding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they have Weeds in their Garden,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100460:35"/>as well as thoſe that do nothing; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who would be at ſo much pains? Thus fooliſhly do People talk of thoſe that pray, and read, and inſtruct their Families, and hear Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they have their Faults, as well as others; wicked Perſons amongſt them, as well as others; their Children and Servants are bad, as well as ours. But they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not, that it is not the whole Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that is over-run with Weeds, as yours is, it is but <hi>here</hi> and <hi>there</hi> a Weed; and as ſoon as they ſpy any, they pluck them up, and do what they can to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their growth and ſpreading.</p>
            <p>There is ſome Difficulty indeed as to thoſe whoſe Lot is caſt into <hi>prayerleſs Families,</hi> who would be glad with all their Hearts, to have the Worſhip of God kept up; but have either no power, or prevalency to bring it about. My Lot is caſt into ſuch an ignorant, worldly, prophane Family, ſays a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Servant, where they call not upon the Name of God from Week to Week, or at moſt, never more than once a Week. If this be the Caſe of <hi>an Apprentice,</hi> and bound by his Parents, who ſhould have choſen better for him; he may bear it the better, as hoping
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100460:35"/>God will not charge it as his Fault. But if you raſhly ingaged your ſelves into ſuch a Family, becauſe it was a place of more Eaſe, or more Profit; you ought to repent, and beg of God forgiveneſs; and be afraid leſt ſome ſpiritual Judgment, and it may be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral too, ſhould follow you. You ought to remove into a better Air, as ſoon as you can conveniently. But let me beg you, as you tender the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and the Credit of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; while you ſtay in ſuch a wicked family, indeavour with utmoſt Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Modeſty, Seriouſneſs, and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, to adorn your Profeſſion; to leave a Conviction in the Conſcience of thoſe with whom you dwell, that <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Godlineſs doth make the beſt Servants.</hi> How ſad is it, if by you who profeſs Religion, your ungodly Maſters or Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Servants ſhould be hardened, and ſtumbled, and prejudiced againſt the holy Ways of God! It may fall out that if you carry it ſo, as to win the Love of all, you ſhall have an Opportunity offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, humbly to ſuggeſt, and urge ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to promote Family-Prayer and Worſhip; and poſſibly obtain to have it begun. Be ſure, however, that you be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100460:36"/>more diligent and conſtant in ſecret Prayer. The leſs help you have in the Family, the more ſhould you redeem to be alone with God. But Servants who value the Welfare of their Souls, and their Improvement in Grace, ſhould take heed what Families they chuſe to dwell in. Do not, out of choice, place your ſelves in a Houſe where God doth not dwell; to which the Curſe of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Word, is threatened. You know he dwells in <hi>the Houſe of Prayer;</hi> His own Houſe is ſuch, and ours ſhould be ſo too; and he inhabits the Praiſes of his People.</p>
            <p>My caſe is yet worſe, may ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; I am <hi>Son to a prayerleſs Father,</hi> and I cannot leave the Houſe; Or I am <hi>Wife</hi> to a Husband that minds not God, or his own Soul, much leſs mine, or any in the Family. The like Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice as was given before to religious Servants, is fit to be taken here; <hi>viz.</hi> to ſpend the more time in <hi>ſecret Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Cloſet Devotion,</hi> and to pray the more earneſtly and fervently for ſuch a Relation, who is the Head of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and yet neglects the Duty of his place. The holy fervent Prayer of a believing Child, or Wife, may help to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100460:36"/>ſave an unbelieving Parent, or Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; It may obtain Grace from God to turn his Heart. In the next Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or under the next worldly Croſs or Diſappointment, or Family-ſtrait and Affliction, you may have a Seaſon offer'd with Meekneſs to ſuggeſt this, and other Duties; and who can tell the Succeſs? However, take heed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn your Profeſſion; and let ſuch near Relations, with whom you are obliged to dwell, be convinced by your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Carriage, of the Amiableneſs and Excellency of a Holy Life, and be made to think and ſpeak well of practical Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Parent,</hi> or <hi>Husband</hi> be either unfit or unwilling to pray in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; can you not obtain that ſome other may do it in his room and ſtead? Though it be the proper Work of <hi>the Maſter of the Family,</hi> yet in many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes another may be ſubſtituted; even an holy <hi>Servant</hi> ſometimes, with the Maſter's leave and deſire. Or, in his Sickneſs or Abſence, I know not why, in divers Caſes, the <hi>Wife,</hi> who is to ſhare in the Government of the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may not perform <hi>Family-Prayer,</hi> at leaſt with thoſe of her own Sex; and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100460:37"/>with all the Family if ſhe be a <hi>Widow;</hi> and if ſhe be a <hi>Wife,</hi> why not in the Husband's Abſence? For if <hi>he</hi> do not his Duty in this particular, what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is there, that ſhe may not be the Mouth of the Family to God in Prayer, rather than it ſhould be omitted?</p>
            <p>Theſe plain things I offer'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended with Seriouſneſs to remove the common Objections, Pleas, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes for the neglect of <hi>Family-Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and touching the Duty of the ſeveral Relations in Religious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. If any may be hereby confirm'd, or convinc'd, I know you will rejoyce with me, and bleſs God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:100460:37"/>
            <head>Of Family Religion.</head>
            <head type="sub">The THIRD LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WIthout farther Preface, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to make good my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, by ſending you the Remainder of my Papers on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, containing ſome <hi>Directions,</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> relating to <hi>Family Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You who are <hi>Heads of Families,</hi> are in the firſt place obliged to be very Careful, and Circumſpect, Serious and Exemplary in your Lives: (you ought to take heed, that you give no Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Vice before <hi>Inferiours.</hi>) They will ſooner Imitate you in what is <hi>Evil,</hi> than <hi>Good.</hi> Let them have no Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement or Countenance given them to Sin, by any thing they ſee you do. You will quickly loſe all Authority,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100460:38"/>and Power to reprove, or ſuppreſs their Evils, if your own Example counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance them in it. It is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that Religion ſhould thrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Children and Servants, where the <hi>Parent</hi> or <hi>Maſter</hi> gives a Pattern of Drunkenneſs, or Lewdneſs, of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, Deceit, and Fraud; or only keeps up the Worſhip of God, to cloak his own Wickedneſs, or ſerve ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Deſign. Wo to thoſe <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> whoſe Children are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of their Impiety, and like enough to follow them (without a wonderful Grace) to their eternal Ruine. <hi>Never Parent had ſuch a wicked Child,</hi> ſaid <hi>a bad Eather</hi> once to <hi>a Rebellious Son;</hi> Yes Sir, replied the Impudent Youth, <hi>My Grandfather had.</hi> Some have inquired for what reaſon the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for Vengeance on the <hi>Children</hi> that mocked him, and ſtiled him <hi>Bald-pate,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.23. when many of them, it is probable, hardly underſtood what they ſaid. The Reaſon aſſigned, is this, becauſe the <hi>Children</hi> learnt that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage from their <hi>Parents;</hi> and God puniſhed the Parents in the Death of the Children, and both at once. Some of the Heathens have been very wary
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100460:38"/>and cautious, not to ſpeak an uncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word in the preſence of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Certainly the Head of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Family is obliged to behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Wiſely</hi> in an upright way, and to walk within his Houſe with <hi>a Perfect Heart, Pſal.</hi> 101.2. and in all things to ſhew himſelf <hi>a Pattern of Good Works, Tit.</hi> 2.7. A prudent, grave, chearful, ſincere Deportment, as becometh Saints, would recommend Religion, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the ſavour of it to all about it. But if you give them never ſo good Counſel, they will ſooner be influenced by a bad Life, than by the beſt of Words. All your good Precepts and Counſels, will be as Water ſpilt on the ground, if not accompanied by a good Example. What you would reprove, and amend in their Words or Actions, let them be ſure to hear nothing of it in your Diſcourſe, and ſee nothing of it in your Practice: You muſt lead them the way in Humility and Charity, in the Government of the Tongue, Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Appetite; in the Redemption of Time, in Prayer, and love to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, and the Ordinances of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:100460:39"/>
            <p>How can a drunken or unrighteous <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Maſter</hi> expect his Children, and Servants ſhould be ſober and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? Can you hope to teach them <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,</hi> and they ſee you are Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate? or <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> when they ſee you cannot govern your Paſſions? They will ſooner learn your Sin, than your Trade. And is not the Money given with ſuch an Apprentice very ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed? One, Two, Three Hundred Pounds, or more, to have them taught to ſerve the Devil, and damn their Souls, by the Example of a wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? But ſuch Maſters ſhall have dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Damnation. Therefore let your own Example teach all your Relations, that Holineſs and Unblamableneſs, in Tongue and Life, which you deſire they ſhould learn and practiſe.</p>
            <p>But beſides your own Example, you are obliged by all other ways to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Spiritual and Eternal Good. You are <hi>worſe than Inſidels,</hi> if you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide not what is <hi>Needful,</hi> and <hi>Fit</hi> for them as to their Temporal Life; much more if you neglect their Souls. O look upon them with Pity and Compaſſion; help them, as knowing their Ignorance, their Temptations, and Danger! Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100460:39"/>they muſt ſhortly die, and be ſaved or periſh for ever. Uſe all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages you have to do them good: Let them not be betrayed to eternal Ruine, by your neglect. Miniſters, by publick Preaching, cannot do ſo much to further their Salvation, as you; and it is very little we can hope to do, without your Aſſiſtance. You can ſpeak (ſharply enough ſometimes) of unfaithful Miniſters, who neglect the Souls of their People; but conſider not your own Guilt and dreadful Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon the like Account. You ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect more Duty ſometimes from <hi>One</hi> Miniſter, than <hi>Six</hi> can perform, while you make no Conſcience of neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your own Duty, in your proper Sphere.</p>
            <p>It will be a dreadful Meeting in the Day of Recompence, to have your Children or Servants to accuſe their Parents and Maſters; ſaying, I was ſo many Years in my Father's Houſe; or I lived ſo long with ſuch a Maſter, who never concerned himſelf about my Soul: I had never been a Servant of Sin, and a Firebrand of Hell, if he had done his part to prevent it. The like will be true of ungodly <hi>Husbands</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:100460:40"/>and <hi>Wives,</hi> who notwithſtanding the Duty and Profeſſion of the deareſt Love, do little or nothing to ſave one another from the Wrath to come. O cruel Husband! O curſed Wife! It was long of <hi>You,</hi> that I am now a loſt, undone Creature; You never did any thing to aſſiſt my Salvation, it was long of <hi>You,</hi> that I came to this Miſerable End; <hi>You</hi> neither by Example, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or Prayer, or Admonition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> diſcovered any Care for your own Soul, or for mine. Yea how many in ſuch Relations, do much to hinder, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Happineſs and Salvation of thoſe, whom they are moſt concerned and obliged to help! For if the one be ungodly, and the other be an awakened ſerious Chriſtian; the <hi>Latter</hi> ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly find the greateſt Oppoſition and Difficulty, and Hinderance in Religion, from him, or her, who ſhould have given the greateſt Help and Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore, that beſides Prayer in your Houſe, you have other Indeavours to uſe, for the Salvation of thoſe that live with you. You mock God by praying for the converſion of Children and Servants, if you do not otherwiſe indeavour it: If you do not indeavour
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100460:40"/>to convince them of their Sin, and of their need of Chriſt and his Grace; if you do not recommend him as the beſt Maſter; and put them in mind of the uncertainty of this Life, and of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Account they muſt give to God another day, of all their Time, and Talents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet this neglect is now ſo common, that they are reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Good Parents,</hi> and <hi>Good Maſters,</hi> who will but give their Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants leave to be good, and go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without them: Who will not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Inferiours from ſerving God. Whereas, you have much to do of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Duty, to
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi>'s Saints Reſt, <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>Sect.</hi> 16.</note> inform their Minds, to furniſh their Memories, to rectify their Wills, to quicken their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to keep tender their Conſciences, and reſtrain their Tongues, and watch over their outward Carriage; to make them hate Sin, and love Holineſs, and prize the Bible, and delight in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and like good Company, and diſlike all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:100460:41"/>
            <p>And to what End hath God given you <hi>The Authority of Parents, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> if not to prevent Sin, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Holineſs in your Families? Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature is ſo corrupt, that (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in ſome few with whom the Spirit of God begins very early, and the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Holy Baptiſm are diſcovered in Childhood) there need to be great Reſtraints put upon it, by thoſe who have Power and Authority over Young People. Your Authority muſt be kept up, leſt you ſhould be deſpiſed by thoſe that you ſhould Rule. Labour therefore to underſtand the Nature, Uſe, and Extent of that Authority, with Relation to all in your Family. And the more you grow in Knowledg and Holineſs, and walk according to the Goſpel-Rule; the better will you preſerve your Authority among all your Inferiours. Humility and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and circumſpect Walking, will enable you to do them the more good, in the uſe of that Power which God has given you. The Indulgence, and Allowance of Children in what is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, you know did highly provoke God in the caſe of <hi>Eli,</hi> and how dear did it coſt him? That <hi>his Sons made themſelves
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:100460:41"/>vile, and he reſtrained them not,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 3.13. You muſt <hi>not let Wickedneſs dwell in your Tabernacle,</hi> Job 11.14. or in thoſe of your Family. They will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Orders, and regard your Commands; if you do not indiſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſe your Authority, by not keeping your diſtance, or ſuffering them to be too bold with you; or on the other hand making them too ſtrange, ſo as to be fearful and diſcouraged, (I here ſpeak eſpecially of Children:) If what you reſolve upon, and order, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding what is good, or forbidding what is evil, you ſee be punctually obſerved, ſtill managing all with Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Love; and manifeſting the Honour of God, and the Intereſt of their Souls, and Salvation, to have been your greateſt Motive. And remember, that Commendation when they do well is as needful, as Reproof and Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when they ſinfully tranſgreſs; which alſo ought to be without Partiality, or the cauſeleſs cockering, or countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of one above the reſt.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid, though with ſome difference, with reſpect to <hi>Your Servants.</hi> Be Juſt, Compaſſionate, and Loving to them, but loſe not your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100460:42"/>as a Maſter: Be Faithful and Affectionate in your Counſeling of them for the good of their Souls. But if they be refractory and ſtubborn, and ſlight your Advice, and go on in Sin, and wax worſe and worſe, and deride ſerious Godlineſs in their Fellow-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; you muſt uſe other Methods, or get rid of them, as ſoon as you can. You are to take care, that Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs dwell not within your Houſe, without Admoniſhing and Reproving of it. You muſt warn them who are anruly, and of others have Compaſſion, making a difference. Some muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked ſharply, others ſave with fear, pulling them out of the Fire, <hi>Jude</hi> 22, 23 Verſes.</p>
            <p>As to thoſe who have Trades and Families, but God hath not bleſſed them with <hi>Children,</hi> or hath taken them away by Death; their Care, and Labour, and Truſt is thereby leſſened, and they ought to be the more careful with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their <hi>Servants.</hi> They have many Conſiderations to keep them from Repining, or Sorrowing much for the want of Children, upon the Account of the Duty, the Pains, the Care, and Grief of Heart, which they are freed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100460:42"/>from: For in this diſſolute Age, how few Children anſwer the Hopes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and Pains of Parents? Or prove Comforts to them when they grow up? If God had given you Children, or prolonged their Lives; what a Life of Trouble and Sorrow might <hi>They</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably have paſſed in this World? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the conſtant Fear you would have had of their Sin and Damnation: which may be put in the Ballance againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertain Comforts</hi> of thoſe who have Children, abſtracting from that Conſolation, which ariſes from the faithful diſcharge of Duty to them.</p>
            <p>More particularly, it is adviſable, with Family Prayer, to joyn <hi>Serious Reading of the Holy Seriptures</hi> every Day, and frequent Catechizing, or Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Inferiours in the Principles of Religion. <hi>Abraham</hi> had ſuch <hi>Trained, Catechized</hi> Servants in his Houſe. <hi>Theſe things that I command thee,</hi> ſays God to his Antient People, <hi>ſhall be in thy Heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently to thy Children,</hi> Deut. 4.9. chap. 11.19. <hi>Teach a Child in the way he ſhould go, and when he is Old, he will not depart from it,</hi> Prov. 4.4. chap. 22.6. 2 Tim. 1.3. Acquaint them by little and little with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100460:43"/>the great Doctrines of Chriſtianity; give them Line upon Line, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept upon Precept, as they are able to receive, and bear it. Acquaint them betimes with the Word, and Works of God, <hi>When you ſit in the Houſe, or walk by the Way, or lie down, or riſe up;</hi> by asking them Queſtions, and putting them upon asking you. <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is approved, and recommended by God in this matter, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>For I know him, that he will command his Children, and his Houſhold after him, that they ſhall keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never diel any Age afford better Helps for <hi>Catechizing,</hi> than this; there being ſo many excellent Catechiſms, or Summaries of Chriſtian Religion, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy printed, and eaſy to be had. If any of you want a Method for Regular Catechizing in your Families, as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon a Lord's-day Evening, or once a Week; let me mention one, which is practiſed by many with good Succeſs, in ſome Counties of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>viz.</hi> Let the Maſter of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begin with a ſhort Invocation of God, praying for his Preſence, Aſſiſtance and Bleſſing; and then ask the younger ſort <hi>Three</hi> Queſtions out of the <hi>Aſſemblies
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100460:43"/>Catechiſm,</hi> and upon each of the three Anſwers, ask the explicatory Queſtions in Mr. <hi>Joſeph Allen's</hi> Catechiſm, or Mr. <hi>Lye</hi>'s, ſo that by anſwering <hi>Yes</hi> or <hi>No,</hi> you will perceive whether they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the matter treated of. After this, read <hi>The fuller Explication</hi> of thoſe <hi>Three</hi> Queſtions in ſome larger Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, as that of Mr. <hi>Thomas Vincent;</hi> and then cloſe with a ſhort Prayer; and if you can, <hi>Sing a Pſalm.</hi> All which may be done in an Hour, and you will find it very profitable both for younger and elder People.</p>
            <p>The reading of the Holy Scriptures frequently in your Families, as well as in your Cloſets, upon the Week-days, as well as upon the Lord's-day, I hope I need not uſe many Arguments to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18. They are able to make us wiſe unto Salvation, and they are ſuitable to every Caſe, that you or yours can be in. They that cannot read, or will not read, or have not ſo much time to read, may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by your reading the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in your Family with them. The <hi>Singing of Pſalms or Hymns,</hi> in Chriſtian Families, where there are enough who are able to joyn in that part of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100460:44"/>is alſo a very commendable and excellent part of Family-Religion, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Let the Word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all wiſdom; teaching and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing one another in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, ſinging with grace in your hearts to the Lord.</hi> Eſpecially on the <hi>Lord's Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I would next ſpeak of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am perſwaded, that no Family-Religion can be duly kept up, without the Sanctification of the <hi>weekly Sabbath.</hi> What the Jews ſaid falſly of Chriſt, we may apply truly enough to many a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and Maſter; <hi>This Man is not of God, for he keepeth not the Sabbath Day,</hi> and takes no Care that his Family with him do ſo. You have many helps to underſtand the Nature of the Duty, and of your Chriſtian Deportment on <hi>that Day,</hi> in publick, private, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. You would do well, the Night before to make ſome Preparation for the Solemnity of that Day; and in the Morning, to poſſeſs your Souls with the Conſideration of the Privilege you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in ſuch weekly Seaſons of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, and paying Homage to him. Serious Godlineſs has never been found to flouriſh in any Soul, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100460:44"/>Houſe, as to any Perſon, or any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, where the ſtrict
<note n="*" place="bottom">See <hi>my Lord Chieſ Juſtice HALES</hi>'s Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Vol.</hi> 1. Directions to his Children, touching the keeping of the <hi>LORD</hi>'s <hi>DAY.</hi>
               </note> Obſervation of the Lord's Day has been neglected. If you begin with God in ſecret, that will prepare you for Family-Worſhip; the private Worſhip of God in your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies will fit you for the publick; and your careful ſerious Attendance on that, will help you to return to the Worſhip of God in your Families, and Cloſets. You ought to methodize, and time theſe Duties ſo, as one may not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere with the other. Sanctify the whole Day to God, improve every part of it; make it not ſhorter than the other Days of the Week, as many do, by ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing later, and going to bed ſooner. Bring as many of your Families to the publick Worſhip with you, as you can. When <hi>Elkanah</hi> went to <hi>ſacrifice to the Lord, he and all his Houſe went with him;</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. And if you recollect, and repeat to them aferwards, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of what you, and they have heard preached, it may promote their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiveneſs in hearing, aſſiſt their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100460:45"/>to retain what they heard, and quicken your own Affections. That by reading the Holy Scriptures, by Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, by repeating Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> your Children and Servants may be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Knowledg of God, his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Works, and Will; in the Knowledg, of themſelves, the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of their Souls, the Nature of Sin, our firſt Apoſtacy, and the ſad Effects of it, our Redemption and Recovery by Jeſus Chriſt, his Perſon, his Offices, his Ordinances and Sacraments, his Promiſes, Faith in him, the Covenant of Grace, the Properties and Privileges of Believers, the Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the next Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, do but ſpend that Day, as knowing how ſmall a part of every Week, <hi>one Day</hi> is to be ſolemnly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in preparing for an Eternal State: do but imploy that Day, under the Senſe of the Value of Immortal Souls, your own and others: And think how near the Judgment-Day may be, when you muſt be accountable to God for all your Time, and eſpecially ſuch ſacred Time. Do but ſpend that Day, as believing the Good or Evil In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence it will have upon all the other
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100460:45"/>Days of the Week; The Affairs of your Souls will thrive, or not thrive, as <hi>the Lord's Day</hi> is ſanctified, or neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The Souls of your Children and Servants, if not minded then, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to be minded on the other Days of the Week: And oftentimes it is found, that even your civil, and ſecular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs do proſper, or not, according to your Care, or Remiſneſs in ſanctifying the Lord's Day.</p>
            <p>Moreover, you ought not only to pray with your Families, and worſhip God with them; but to obſerve the Neceſſities of every one in particular, and heartily <hi>to pray for them in ſecret.</hi> You would have more Comfort in your Family-Relations, and God more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from them; did you more fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beg of God the Grace which you and they do need. <hi>Monica</hi> the Mother of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> had gracious Anſwers to her Requeſts to God, both for her Husband and her Son. How can you ſtrive with God in Prayer for your own Souls, and not remember to do the like for thoſe whoſe Souls are committed to your Care? O that my Son may live to thee! O that my Daughters may not die for ever! O that my Servants may
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:100460:46"/>not ſerve the Devil! O that there may not be a Son of Perdition, nor a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Belial,</hi> under my Roof! <hi>Have mercy on me, O Lord,</hi> ſays the Woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> unto <hi>Chriſt: For my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is grievouſly vexed with a Devil.</hi> A certain Man, at another time, comes kneeling to him, ſaying, <hi>Lord have mercy upon my Son. for he is a Lunatick, and ſore vexed: For oftentimes he falls into the Fire, and oftentimes into the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Such Prayers had ſucceſs for the Cure of bodily Evils, and may rather be hoped to have ſo, for ſpiritual ones. If the Caſe of your Children reſemble this, that any of them fall ſometimes into the Fire of Luſt, ſometimes into the Water of Drunkenneſs, ſometimes into this Sin, ſometimes into that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurried, and led captive by the Devil; beg that God would diſpoſſeſs Satan, and that he would have mercy on them, and bring them to themſelves. You know not what effect your Prayers may have while you live; nor of what Advantage a Stock of Prayers, laid up, may be unto your Children, after your Death. The largeſt Portion, the faireſt Inheritance, or Eſtate you can leave them, may be a much leſs Kindneſs.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:100460:46"/>Your Intereſt in the Covenant, and hearty Prayers for their Salvation, is a Treaſure, they cannot ſufficiently value. Whereas a wicked Father <hi>lays up Iniquity for his Children,</hi> as you have the Expreſſion, <hi>Job</hi> 21.19, 20. He may ſtore up Riches, and God treaſures up Wrath: And upon Imitation of their Father's Sins, God fills up the Meaſure of their Judgment, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.48, 50.</p>
            <p>While you neglect not Family and ſecret Prayer in theſe reſpects, you muſt likewiſe remember to obſerve what <hi>Anſwers,</hi> God at any time gives to ſuch Prayers; What ſerious Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are made on the Minds and Hearts of Children or Servants; how their Knowledge and Grace do increaſe and grow; what Convictions the Spirit hath wrought on any of them; who is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and how God hath proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered your ſecular Indeavours, how he favours your Diligence in your Calling; but eſpecially how he rewards your Faithfulneſs to the <hi>Souls</hi> of Inferiours. If any of your Children be good, or hopeful, though one it may be, or more be not; bleſs God for ſuch a Mercy. Let not your ſorrowful Complaints as to <hi>one,</hi> ſilence your Gratitude for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:100460:47"/>Grace manifeſted in another. All your Children were born in Sin, and might have lived and died in Sin; but you can ſay, though I have a <hi>Cain,</hi> I have a righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> I have a <hi>Shem</hi> as well as a <hi>Cham,</hi> a <hi>Jacob</hi> as well as an <hi>Eſau,</hi> a <hi>Solomon</hi> as well as an <hi>Abſalom</hi> or <hi>Amnon.</hi> God hath anſwered my Prayers, and bleſſed my Endeavours as to one or more, though not as to all: I will wait, and pray in Hope as to them alſo. By thus taking notice what Anſwers of Prayer you have upon this Account, you will know the better how to frame your Petitions to God for them, and to order your Counſels, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and farther Indeavours for their good: You will know what you have to acknowledge, and be thankful for, and what you have to lament, and beg in <hi>Family-Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Management of that, Care is to be taken to chuſe the <hi>fitteſt Time.</hi> A good Man will indeavour to order his Spiritual Affairs with Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well as his Temporal ones. In Family-Worſhip you ſhould indeavour to be <hi>ſhort, diſtinct, methodical,</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious;</hi> and not make ſuch Duties <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long,</hi> leſt ſome of the Family be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:100460:47"/>to ſay, Behold, what a Wearineſs is it? Labour to be ſerious and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, though ordinarily you be but ſhort: you may be longer on the Lord's Day. Be <hi>ſerious,</hi> I ſay, and <hi>affectionate:</hi> for he that is the Mouth of others to God in Prayer, if his Heart be drowſie, they who join with him are not like to be affected. You ought diſcreetly to chuſe <hi>the Time</hi> alſo: In the Morning you will find, if it be deferred till ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſuch a <hi>Buſineſs</hi> be firſt diſpatch'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or if it be not one of the <hi>firſt</hi> things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one in the Morning; you will find ſomething or other intervene, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it altogether. And in ſuch Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies where it can conveniently be done, before Supper; for the Evening is the moſt deſirable Time. Many never kneel down to pray in their Families at Night, till they are fitter to lie down upon their Beds.</p>
            <p>In the ordering of theſe things, let <hi>Husbands</hi> and <hi>Wives,</hi> who would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Salvation of each others Souls, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ointly concur to promote Godlineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their Families. Their firſt Care ſhould be to indeavour the Salvation of each others Souls. For this they have Scripture-Incouragement, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:100460:48"/>7.16. <hi>For what knoweſt thou, O Wife, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy Husband? Or how knoweſt thou, O Man, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy Wife?</hi> It is true, no feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chriſtian would deliberately chuſe to be ſo nearly related to one, that is a ſtranger to Chriſt: And they who are ſo related, ought to beg God For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs for their ſinful Raſhneſs. But if they find themſelves miſtaken in their Choice in that reſpect, they muſt uſe the greater Care to perſwade them to be ſuch, as they ſuppoſed them to have been: Remembring however, that if they cannot as yet love them, as <hi>real Saints,</hi> they muſt yet love them, as <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands</hi> and <hi>Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how hopefully may Religion be carried on in the Family, where <hi>both</hi> are devoted to God, and married to Chriſt! How ſhould (and may) they build up one another in their Holy Faith, watch over each other, ſtudy their Tempers and Diſpoſitions, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort one another daily with Meekneſs and Wiſdom, and ſtrengthen one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Hands in the Diſcharge of their reſpective Duties to Inferiours; indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the utmoſt Union in this Work, leſt, through the want of it,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:100460:48"/>their Authority be weakened, and their Endeavours be fruſtrate of any good Succeſs. The Endeavours of both are required: And if Covenant-Mercy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from Parents to Children, 'tis on this Condition, that during their <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority,</hi> they take care to bring them up in the Knowledge, Nurture and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord. When they come to be adult, or grown up, there is another Condition on the part of the Children, that they conſent to the Terms of the Covenant, and willingly come under the Band of it. But <hi>both Parents</hi> are concern'd to bring up their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for God. <hi>Men</hi> ſhould not caſt all the Care of Children, and Servants on their <hi>Wives;</hi> and Women ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, as Matter of Duty, their joint In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the religious Government of the Family. I wiſh it were not a very frequent Caſe, that they, who ſhould rule, are the moſt unruly part; and the Cauſe, that the Family is ungodly, and ungoverned.</p>
            <p>There is a great Latitude in the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Parents to their Children, to take care of them in Infancy, to dedicate them to God betimes, and bring them under the viſible Band of the Covenant
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:100460:49"/>by <hi>Raptiſm;</hi> and to teach them the meaning of it, as ſoon as capable; to keep them in ſubjection while young; to encourage them in all that is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and praiſe-worthy, and good; and lovingly, and ſeaſonably reprove them for what is evil; to diſpoſe of them with Wiſdom and Care, as to their Schools, Callings, and Marriage, according to your Rank and Station, in the beſt Manner you can. And therein to conſider the Intereſt of their Souls, as well as their temporal Welfare, and prefer it. Beg of God to teach you the true <hi>Medium</hi> between the Errours of Education, on either <hi>Extreme;</hi> either <hi>that</hi> of humouring them in Vanity, and indulging them in Sin, or <hi>that</hi> of Frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardneſs, Harſhneſs, and too much Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity. If your own Parents be living, give your Children an Example of the Honour and Obedience you expect from them, by your becoming Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Grand Parents.</p>
            <p>If you would recommend, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Religion among Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, there is one thing I would beg of you, that you take heed never to ſpeak of God and Sacred things, without the utmoſt <hi>Seriouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Reverence.</hi> If
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:100460:49"/>you do not poſſeſs their Minds with an Awe and Reverence of God, and Chriſt, and the Holy Scriptures, and the Life to come, you will do them little good. You ſhould begin betime to do this. Mothers eſpecially may drop Inſtruction into their Children, as ſoon almoſt as their Milk: At leaſt you may teach them to pray, as ſoon as they begin to prattle. <hi>Timothy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that Knowledg of the Faith, in his Childhood, from his Mother and Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, (though his Father was a Greek or a Pagan, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.1.) which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he publickly profeſs'd, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered unto.</p>
            <p>And much of the good or bad Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon their Minds, from what you ſay, will depend upon the Manner of your ſpeaking: Your words muſt diſcover your honourable Thoughts of God, and Holineſs, and Holy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They will be apt to like what you commend. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour therefore to ſpeak of Sin, and of wicked Men, with loathing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; that they may ſee <hi>your Judgment,</hi> and learn to form <hi>their own.</hi> The way to win them betimes to the Fear of God, and Hatred of that which is Evil,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:100460:50"/>is frequently to repreſent, in your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, how fafe, how profitable, how honourable, and pleaſant a Life that of <hi>ſerious Godlineſs</hi> is. Hereby you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, or cure their Prejudices concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning practical Religion, as a melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, burdenſome thing. And take heed what <hi>Books</hi> they read, and what <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> they keep, leſt their Minds be poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and corrupted by ill Principles, and their Hearts inticed and drawn to Sin; and ſo all your Inſtructions fail of Succeſs. Without ſuch Care 'tis in vain to put up Bills to Miniſters, Week after Week, to pray for your dead Children, whoſe Souls you your ſelves do murder by your Negligence, or ill Example.</p>
            <p>But your Counſels and Diſcourſe, back'd by a Holy <hi>Example</hi> to inforce them, may do much good; and will if theſe go together: For if <hi>Inferiours</hi> ſee you to be unjuſt, deceitful, drunken, wanton, cruel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all your ſerious Talk will do them harm, rather than good. Eſpecially if you do not carry it well in your Relations to them; if Parents be very paſſionate, and haſty with their Children; if Maſters be bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, and hard-hearted to their <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:100460:50"/>and remember not how it was with them when <hi>they</hi> were <hi>Servants:</hi> I mean not ſo much, how they fared, as how they deſired, and wiſh'd to have been uſed, under their Apprentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>And of all the ſerious things which may be proper to be recollected; there is hardly any thing of greater Moment, than to inſtil often into their Minds, the value and worth of <hi>Time.</hi> That they may be brought to hate <hi>Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and not care to miſpend one Hour: But as they grow more capable of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving it, may be ſtill imployed. You cannot inſiſt too often upon the <hi>Brevity,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty</hi> of our little <hi>Time</hi> on Earth; the Swiftneſs and Irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of it, and the Conſequence of redeeming it well or ill, in order to our future Account. The Devil is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſure of thoſe, who are brought up in <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> and put no value upon their <hi>precious Time.</hi> Urge this therefore to Inferiours, and help them to improve their Time, and to begin every Day with <hi>ſecret Prayer alone,</hi> and to imploy the other part of it, in what is ſuitable to their Age, Capacity, Condition, and Relation.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:100460:51"/>
            <p>You would do well to put them upon <hi>ſecret Prayer;</hi> to adviſe your Children and Servants, and charge them to pray <hi>alone</hi> every Day, as well as be willing to join in Family-Prayer. You ought alſo to teach them, by Word and by Example, to beg a Bleſſing on their Food, at the uſual Seaſons of Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſeriouſly to return Thanks afterwards. We depend on God for <hi>our Daily Bread:</hi> And our Bleſſed Saviour did never eat himſelf, or feed others at his Table, but he bleſſed, and gave thanks, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.6, 7. So the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 27.25. and by Prayer and Thankſgiving is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature ſanctified, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>It will be of great Moment in order to a religious, well-ordered Family, to be very careful <hi>whom</hi> you admit to dwell with you. The Caſe may be ſo ſtated, it is true, that you muſt dwell with ſuch as ſcorn, and deſpiſe Family-Religion, and Worſhip; But take heed leſt you ſinfully chuſe ſuch Relations, and ſuch Inhabitants. It may be, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> thought that <hi>Michal,</hi> whom he knew came of a bad Stock, might be prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with by him, to join in the Worſhip of God, and in time be brought over to what he deſired; but ſhe deſpiſed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:100460:51"/>him in her Heart, and mocked at his Zeal, and proved a Snare and a Croſs, and made him repent his Choice. Wo to him, who hath a <hi>Philiſtin</hi> in his Boſom, as <hi>Samſon</hi> had. <hi>Marriage</hi> is the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-point of Life: Your future Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and your Eternal Intereſt, are greatly concerned therein. We find the Wickedneſs, and Ruin of ſeveral of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> laid at this Door; that they married into a wicked Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Such a One,</hi> he had a Wife of the Houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and was quickly drawn off from God, by one who had a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ahab</hi> to her Father, and a curfed <hi>Jezabel</hi> to her Mother; and ſhe ſtirr'd him up to work Wickedneſs, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.25.</p>
            <p>A due Care on this Account is to be had in the Choice of <hi>Servants</hi> alſo: Such are to be preferr'd, who by <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and, as far as you can judge, by <hi>Inclination</hi> too, will be willing to ſerve God, and rejoice in the Helps they may have to do ſo, in a religious Family. And how orderly and beautiful is <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily-Worſhip,</hi> where all in the Houſe do heartily join in it? You complain, you cannot bring your Servants to do what you deſire, as to Matters of Religion,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:100460:52"/>when it may be you had nothing of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in your Eye, in the Choice of Servants. It may be for a ſmall Sum leſs with an Apprentice, or for the ſame Wages to another Servant, you might have had one, whoſe Education, and Inclinations would have been more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging; and who would thank God to enjoy ſuch Advantages, for the Knowledg and Service of God, as he might have in your Houſe. Servants alſo in diſpoſing themſelves; and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> in the diſpoſing their Children, ought to conſider this. A wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter will commonly chuſe wicked Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and make them worſe. <hi>When a Ruler</hi> (of an Houſe, or Town, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) <hi>hearkeneth to Lies,</hi> (or is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wicked) <hi>all his Servants are wicked, Prov.</hi> 29.12. Such a one can't endure the conſtant Reproof, that is given him by the good Converſation even of a Servant: And therefore will deſire no more Religion in a Servant, than not to be unfaithful to his Truſt. I wiſh there be not ſome <hi>Maſters,</hi> (even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe, who would be accounted <hi>Religious)</hi> who are ſhy of chuſing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that have the Character of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſo;</hi> contrary to <hi>David</hi>'s Practice,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:100460:52"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.4, 5, 7. It is true, ſome that have been well educated, have proved very ill afterwards; and Maſters have found themſelves miſtaken, after all their Care in this Matter: But if they did their Duty, to make the beſt Choice, and uſe the beſt Endeavours they could, they may have Peace and Quiet in their own Minds, when they meet with a Diſappointment; which otherwiſe they cannot.</p>
            <p>They ought to look to it, whom they admit into their Families; unleſs they value their particular Calling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their General one: For who can tell the Miſchief, that <hi>one bad Servant</hi> may do in a Houſe? <hi>One Sinner deſtroys much good:</hi> as one <hi>Joſeph</hi> may bring a Bleſſing upon a Family, and upon all that his Maſter hath in the Houſe. You can hardly expect, that God ſhould ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed you with a Bleſſing in what you undertake, when you care not with what Tools you work, or whom you imploy: And in the Nature of the thing, there is little reaſon to hope, that they, who are <hi>falſe</hi> to God, and to their own Souls, will ordinarily be <hi>faithful</hi> to you. We read of thoſe who were no good Men, viz. <hi>Laban,</hi> and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:100460:53"/>
               <hi>Potiphar,</hi> &amp;c. who have thrived the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for taking good Servants into their Families; but I no where read of a good Man, that was the better for a wicked Servant: We have ſad Experience eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But the Welfare and the Comfort of religious Families, depends not wholly on the Duty of the Heads of it; They who are <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>Servants,</hi> are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thankfully to improve the Bleſſing of Religious <hi>Parents,</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> and faithfully to do their Duty in each Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Without a wonderful Change by the Grace of God, you will never be good <hi>Parents</hi> to your own Children, (if you live to have any) if you are not good in the Relation of Children. The ſame may be ſaid for Servants: Nor are they like to be <hi>good Husbands</hi> or <hi>Wives,</hi> who were not <hi>good</hi> in their former Relation as <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi> Neither are ſuch who are not good in their Family-Relations like to be ſo in any other: Either good <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> in a <hi>Town,</hi> or good <hi>Members</hi> in a <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the <hi>State. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi> a Rebellious Child, proved a Traiterous Subject: <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> diſobedient Children, proved ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:100460:53"/>and ſacrilegious Prieſts; ſo in other Inſtances.</p>
            <p>Let Children <hi>honour</hi> and obey their Parents in the Lord: See that there be inward Reverence, Reſpect, and Love: Deſpiſe not their Perſons; ſlight not their Inſtructions, Rebukes, or lawful Commands, or Government. Take heed of ſpeaking contemptuouſly of either of them. <hi>He that curſeth Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let him die the Death,</hi> Levit. 20.9. <hi>His Lamp ſhall</hi> be put out in Darkneſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.20. You ſhould prize their Counſels, delight in their Preſence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in their Company, ſympathize with them in their Sorrows or Joys, and readily deny your ſelves for their Sakes. The Expreſſions of <hi>outward Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> from Children to Parents, by the Diſſoluteneſs of the Age, are almoſt out of Faſhion: Such as riſing up, and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bare before them, (which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the Younger, unto ſuch as are their Fathers only by Age, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.31.) to bow before them, and deſire their Bleſſing or Prayers, to ſpeak alway with reſpect to them, and of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Honour that conſiſts in <hi>Obedience,</hi> may be expreſſed many ways; as by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content to obey their lawful Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:100460:54"/>though in the meanneſt Services; to be content to have their own Wills croſſed, that the Will of their Parents may be fulfilled; by not marrying without their Knowledge, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and by ſubmitting to their juſt Reproofs, Rebukes, and Corrections; and obeying them eſpecially in the things of God, and for the good of their Souls. There is an <hi>Honour</hi> due to <hi>Parents,</hi> which conſiſts in <hi>Thankfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>Recompence:</hi> Readily ſerving them, and ſupplying their outward Wants, comforting them in their Sorrows, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Sickneſs, Old-Age; being ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous for their Safety, and Welfare, concern'd for their Reputation and Good-Name, praying daily for them; and plentifully, freely, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly providing for them, according to your Ability, and their Need. As <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> did when advanc'd in the Court of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> This is not <hi>Juſtice</hi> only, but <hi>Piety. Let them learn to ſhow Piety at home,</hi> and <hi>requite their Parents,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.4. And our Lord reproves the Seribes and Phariſees, who by their corrupt Doctrines would diſpenſe with Children from ſuch an Obligation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.5, 6. Such Children then who are a Grief to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:100460:54"/>their Parents, or purloin their Goods, or waſte their Eſtates, or do not to their utmoſt miniſter to the Supply of their Wants, do ſo far fail of their Duty. The Children of <hi>Religious Parents,</hi> are eſpecially bound to pay them Honour; and ſo to walk, as to reflect Honour on them; imitating their good Examples, thanking God for his ſpecial Mercies to their Parents, while they lived, doing what they can to honour them at their Death; pleading with God the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Relation of their Parents, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Bleſſing on themſelves, as their Off-ſpring; and faithfully adhering to the Truth, Worſhip, and Ways of God, as their Holy Parents did before them.</p>
            <p>This Honour is due to Parents whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Rich or Poor, Wiſe or Weak, whether in an honourable Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World, or in meaner Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whether in vigorous Health, or bowed down under Sickneſs, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirmities of Old-Age: Remember ſtill they are your Parents.</p>
            <p>It is a Mercy you ought to be very thankful for, to have Religious Parents, and live in a Religious Family. It is a Prize in your Hands, you muſt give an Account of: And a ſad Account it will
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:100460:55"/>be, if you remain ignorant of God, and Rebels againſt Chriſt, under thoſe Advantages to know, and obey him, which others want. How unthankful are you, if you value it not as a Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege? What work for the Worm of Conſcience do you provide, if you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it not! You might have been born of ſuch Parents, as would have wholly neglected the Salvation of your Souls; or you might have been caſt into ſome Atheiſtical Families, where God is not worſhiped from Week to Week. Few are ſenſible enough of the Obligation they are under to God, by being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated as <hi>Husband,</hi> or <hi>Wife,</hi> as a <hi>Child</hi> or a <hi>Servant,</hi> to ſuch as truly fear God.</p>
            <p>I would here call ſuch Children to <hi>Repentance,</hi> who have neglected, and failed in their Duty to Parents. Let grown Perſons reflect on their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Youth, when they lived with their Parents, and ſince. Have you not been Stubborn and Rebellious, Irreverent, and diſreſpectful in your Carriage to one, or both of them? Have you not ſecretly deſpiſed them in your Hearts? or openly publiſhed their Infirmities? Have you not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:100460:55"/>diſobeyed their lawful Commands? or ſlighted their wholſom Admonitions? Have you not denyed, or been back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to Aſſiſt and Comfort them? Have you not ſecretly coveted their Eſtates, before their Death? or deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it might be quickly? Did you honour them, inwardly with a good Conſcience, from the Love of God, and the ſenſe of his Authority? Let us call our ſelves to an account, and renew our Repentance before God, for ſuch Sins, that his Pardoning Grace may prevent his Threatned Wrath. And let us take heed to live hereafter as the Children of ſuch, of whom God was not aſhamed to be called their God.</p>
            <p>Remember the Advantages of your being thus related to Holy Parents: for Temporal Bleſſings, <hi>Iſhmael, Solomon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam,</hi> and others are Inſtances of the kindneſs of God to Children upon the account of their Fathers. But you ſtand faireſt for Spiritual and Eternal Bleſſings, you are Children of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and Members of the Viſible Church of Chriſt, the Bleſſing of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, I will be thy God,</hi> which reached unto his Seed, being now come upon us
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:100460:56"/>
               <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Gal. 3.14. You have many <hi>Helps</hi> to ſerious Godlineſs, which others have not: You have many <hi>Hindrances</hi> removed, which make it more difficult for others, who deſcend from wicked Parents, and live in Ignorant, Irreligious Families. You have more Knowledg of God and Chriſt, of Sin and Duty. And uſually the Spirit of Grace begins more early with ſuch Children, and follows them with more Calls, Offers, Invitations, Strivings, Convictions; and leaves them not till they are Profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, Deſperate, and Reſolved in Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs: whereof <hi>Iſhmael</hi> a Scoffer, <hi>Eſau</hi> a Profane Perſon, and the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (who filled up the meaſure of their Iniquity, by Rejecting and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Lord of Glory) are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Examples.</p>
            <p>Remember your Relation, and think what God and all the World expects from you. There is a great Privilege belonging by Goſpel-grant to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Holy, Covenanted Parents, if they do not forfeit it, by forſaking, and practically diſavowing <hi>their Fathers God.</hi> If you will own him, he will be <hi>Your God,</hi> as well as <hi>Theirs.</hi> He hath an early preventive Intereſt in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:100460:56"/>you, upon which you may lay your Claim to him as <hi>Your God,</hi> if you will devote your ſelves to him, and ſtand to his Covenant. To be ungodly Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Holy Parents is the greateſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs that can be. <hi>Be aſtoniſhed O ye Heavens at this!</hi> Jer. 2.12. That any Perſons, or People ſhould caſt off their God. <hi>Thine own Friend, and thy Father's Friend forſake not,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> much leſs <hi>thy Father's God.</hi> How re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful will be your Wickedneſs, if you are not better than others! If you who are the Children of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, become the Children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, by doing his Works! Shall there be a ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmael</hi> come out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Houſe, or a profane <hi>Eſau</hi> from <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Family, a rebellious <hi>Abſalom,</hi> or a filthy <hi>Amnon</hi> be found in the Family of the Holy <hi>David?</hi> God forbid that any of you ſhould find or force the way to <hi>Hell,</hi> out of ſuch Houſes, where God is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhiped. Certainly a Wicked Child of Religious Parents is one of the moſt miſerable Spectacles in the World. He is within the Viſible Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of God, devoted to him, made acquainted with his Duty, and can have no excuſe for his Sin. What
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:100460:57"/>Aggravatious hath ſuch a one's Guilt! They muſt have ſtifled more Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and reſiſted more Grace, than others. And how ſure and ſevere will be their Condemnation! when all the Prayers, and Pains of Holy Parents ſhall witneſs againſt them! and God account ſuch Children, as the Children of the <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> or <hi>Arabian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And have you no Concern for, or Love to your Parents? Conſider how wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Children embitter all the Comforts of their good Parents. <hi>A Father of a Fool,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe Man, <hi>bath no joy,</hi> Prov. 17.21. While Parents are in bitterneſs for a diſſolute Child, they cannot have that Joy and Comfort in one another, which otherwiſe they might: nor in the other Children, who are more hopeful: The whole Family is Afflicted, and Diſturbed. The Grace of God, by which they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their own Corruptions, gives them not ſo much Comfort as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when they ſee the Sin they have mortified and forſaken, break out, and reign in any of their Children. Nor can they rejoyce in <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as otherwiſe, when according to the Word of God, they hope and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:100460:57"/>believe he is their Friend and Father, and by the ſame Word know he is an Enemy to this or the other Son, or Daughter, and that the Wrath of God abideth on them: And that if they get to Heaven themſelves, ſuch of their Children are not like to follow them there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> take heed of their Carriage towards <hi>One another.</hi> Let them indeavour Concord, and Union, and Love; and avoid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and Falling out, and the uſing of provoking, exaſperating Language to one another. Let them help one another, as they can, in Health and Sickneſs, and take each others Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment as their own. Let them watch over one another, as to the Sins, and Temptations they are moſt in danger of. Let them beware of vain unprofitable Diſcourſe, and Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and moſt carefully put away all filthy corrupt Communication, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may poiſon the Souls of one another. Let them tenderly bear with one anothers Failings, and prudently conceal one anothers Faults, (where the Concealment of them tends not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:100460:58"/>to the Wrong of the Parent or Maſter, or of any other; and where the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them will but ſtir up Strife.) This would alſo help to promote <hi>Family Religion.</hi> I deſire and pray that theſe plain haſty Thoughts, may be ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable to that purpoſe. With that Hope, I commend them to the Divine Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and you to his Grace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence: Let us unite in the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that <hi>whatever others do, we with our Houſe, will ſerve the Lord,</hi> and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the God of <hi>our Fathers;</hi> and in that way and manner as to <hi>Our Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> wherein we have, beſides their Example, ſo much other Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Holy Scriptures, and Reaſon, and the Practice of the beſt Men. I am with Reſpect, and Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:100460:58"/>
            <head>APPENDIX, CONTAINING Rules of good Advice FOR OUR <hi>Chriſtian &amp; Civil Carriage,</hi> Moſtly from Biſhop <hi>HALL's Epiſtles.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>LET us begin with Him, who is the <hi>Firſt</hi> and the <hi>Laſt:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your ſelf aright con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, without whom, in vain do we know all things. Be acquainted with your Redeemer, who paid the price of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption on Earth, and now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes
<pb facs="tcp:100460:59"/>in Heaven; without whom we have nothing to do with God, or he with us. Adore him in your Thoughts, Love him with all your Heart, and Truſt him with your Souls. Renew your ſight of him every day, and his of you. Call your ſelves to often Reckonings; caſt up your Debts, Payments, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Wants, Expences, Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Think not your ſet De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions troubleſome; yield not to ſuch a Thought; take not eaſy Denials of your ſelf, and beware of Self-flattery. Think all God's outward Favours and Proviſions the beſt for you; your own Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Actions the meaneſt. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not your Mind to be a Drudge or Wanton; Exerciſe it ever, but overcharge it not. Every Day take a View of your laſt, as what may prove ſo. In all your Buſineſs look through the World to God; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is your Level, let him be your Scope. Offer not your ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:100460:59"/>either to Honour or Labour, let both ſeek you. So frame your ſelf to the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Company,</hi> that you may neither ſerve it, nor ſullenly neglect it; and yield ſo far as that you may not betray your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or countenance Evil. Let your Words be few and digeſted: It is a ſhame for the Tongue to cry the Heart Mercy, much more to caſt it ſelf on the uncertain pardon of other men's Ears. There are but two things, which a Chriſtian is charged to buy, and not to ſell, <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> both ſo precious that we muſt purchaſe them at any rate. So uſe your <hi>Friends,</hi> as thoſe which ſhould be Perpetual, may be Changeable. While you are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your ſelf, there is no danger; but Thoughts once uttered muſt ſtand to Hazard. Do not hear from your ſelf, what you would be loth to hear from others. Give the Eye and Ear full ſcope in what is good, for they let Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb facs="tcp:100460:60"/>into the Mind, but reſtrain the <hi>Tongue;</hi> few Men have repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them of ſilence. In all ſerious Matters, take Counſel of Days, and Nights, and Friends; and let Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ripen your Purpoſes; never hope to gain ought by ſuddenneſs. The firſt Thoughts may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, the ſecond are wiſer. Serve Truth and Honeſty ever, though without apparent Wages; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence is ſure, if ſlow. As in Apparel, ſo in Actions; conſider not ſo much what is good, as what becomes you. Excuſe not your own Evil, agravate not that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and if you love <hi>Peace,</hi> avoid Cenſures, Compariſons, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, and Evil Speaking. Out of good Men chooſe Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, of Acquaintance, Friends, of Friends, Familiars; after Trial, admit them; and after Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, change them not. Do not alway your Beſt: it is neither wiſe nor ſafe for a Man ever to ſtand on
<pb facs="tcp:100460:60"/>the top of his Strength. Be ever below your ſelf, if you would be above the Expectation of others. Expend according to your Purſe, not after your Mind, or the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Neighbours. Rather ſmother your Griefs and Wants as you may, than be either Querulous, or Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate: Frequent Suits, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints are weariſom to a Friend. Let not your Face belie your Heart, nor alway tell tales out of it. In all your Reckonings for the World, caſt up ſome Croſſes that appear not; either they will come, or may. Let your Suſpicions be Charitable; your Truſt fearful; your Cenſures ſure. Give way to the Anger of Great Men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom you have no Fence: patiently bear the Inconveniencies you cannot mend; and make the beſt of what muſt be. If the World ſmile upon you, with double care look to your Soul, for there is more danger in Good than Evil.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:100460:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the Angel in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SOme Account of the Holy <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of Mr. <hi>Henry Gearing:</hi> Who died, <hi>January</hi> the 4th. 1693/4. Aged 61. With the <hi>Trial</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of a Real Chriſtian, collected out of his Papers, for the Examination of himſelf: From which ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Particulars are added, for the <hi>Inſtruction, Encouragement,</hi> and <hi>Imitation</hi> of Chriſtians. By Mr. <hi>John Shower,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Tempting Chriſt: By Mr. <hi>John Shower,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Slater</hi>'s Sermon on the Funeral of Mr. <hi>John Reynolds</hi> Miniſter, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>—His Sermon on the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Richard Fincher,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>—On the Thankſgiving Day, <hi>Oct.</hi> 27. 1692. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Giles Firmin</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Rich. Davis.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen of <hi>London, January</hi> the 30th. 1693/4. By <hi>W. Stephens,</hi> B.D. Rector of <hi>Sutton</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> Sermon on Mr. <hi>Steels</hi> Funeral. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſcellanea Sacra,</hi> Containing Scriptural Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Divine Breathings, Occaſional Reflections, and Sacred Poems. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aickins</hi> Engliſh Grammar; or the Engliſh Tongue reduced to Grammatical Rules. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There will be ſhortly Publiſhed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Slaters</hi> Diſcourſe of Family Religion, in 18 Sermons. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> Diſcourſe of Family Religion, Written and Publiſhed at the requeſt of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Miniſters of <hi>London.</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Right of the Children of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in the Covenant, againſt Mr. <hi>Hercules Collins,</hi> By Mr. <hi>Mence</hi> of <hi>Wapping.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
